well
well
then
luego
family
family
And muscle sig
Ve Kas sig
euro
euro
okay
okay
all
all
Good night
晚安
Today we are very happy to invite researcher Wang Zhonghe
今天我們非常高興請到汪中和研究員
Let's help us interpret a topic that has been very, very lively recently
來幫我們解讀一下最近實事上非常非常熱鬧的一個題目
How to deal with global warming was held in Paris about a month ago
大概一個多月前在巴黎開了一個全球暖化如何因應
So today Dr. Wang can help us very well. How should we respond personally?
所以今天汪博士可以幫我們很好的我們個人應該怎麼因應
He will explain the data very clearly
對於數據上他會交代得非常的清楚
Dr. Wang's expertise is in stable isotropic geochemical analysis
汪博士的專長是在穩定同位數地球化學分析
Dr. Wang is now a researcher at the Earth Institute
汪博士現在是地球所的研究員
He is also the director of the secretariat of our Academia Sinica
也是我們中央研究院秘書處的處長
so he should be very busy
所以他應該是非常忙碌
Come on one night and tell us about these things
播一個晚上來跟我們解說這些事
Grateful
非常感激
Well, his research field is actually very broad.
那他的研究領域其實也很廣
It has a lot to do with climate warming
跟這個氣候暖化非常有關係
There is still water temperature before the warming environment
氣候暖化環境邊前還有水溫
I believe you often see him on TV too
我相信大家在電視上也常常看到他上電視
Talk about the issue of water resources
講這個水資源的問題
The precursor of the earthquake and so on
那地震的前兆等等
This is all within the scope of his research
這都是他的研究範圍之內
He graduated from campus university in 1984
他是1984年從校園大學
I returned to Taiwan after getting my Ph.D.
拿了博士以後就回到台灣
just go back to Academia Sinica
就直接回到中研院
So he is also in Academia Sinica
所以他在中研院也
30 years
30年
32 years
32年
Well, not only is he here, except for the Academia Sinica
那他不但在這其實除了中研院之外
He is also in the National Taiwan University Center for Global Change
他也在台灣大學全球變遷中心
National Chengchi University General Studies Center
政治大學通識中心
central university
中央大學
Hydrology and marine science research units
學水文及海洋科學研究等等單位
part time
兼職
So what I read just now is related to his specialty.
所以剛剛我唸的這些都是跟他的專長有關
So later if you are interested
所以待會如果大家有興趣的話
Can
可以
you can ask him well
可以好好的問問他
The topic he gave us today is global warming and disaster prevention and response
今天他給我們的題目是全球暖化及防災因應
So what we just said about this summit in Paris
那我們剛剛講說這個巴黎的峰會的話
to talk about global warming
就是討論全球暖化
How to deal with disasters has not been mentioned
還沒有提到這個如何防災因應
OK, we welcome Dr. Wang
好 我們歡迎王博士
Thank you to the vice president, the secretary-general, Mr. Li, and all the distinguished guests.
謝謝副院長還有秘書長李老師跟各位貴賓
Colleagues
各位同仁
It is my great honor to be present at our Knowledge Feast in January 2016 today
我今天非常榮幸在2016年我們1月份的知識饗宴
Let everyone be the first to report our climate warming
跟大家先報告我們氣候暖化
A trend we now call global warming
我們現在叫全球暖化它的一個趨勢
And the impact we will face under this trend
以及在這個趨勢之下我們會面到的衝擊
what we should have
我们应该有的因应
First of all, let me review with you
首先我就跟大家回顾一下
our past year
我们过去的这一年
we all say 2015
我们都说2015年
it is our earth has history
它是我们地球有历史
Since the temperature measurement
开始做温度量测以来
hottest year
最热的一年
this year
这一年来
we just said
我们说刚刚讲了说
We use five indicators to tell you
我们用五个指标跟大家讲说
why is it so unique
为什么它那么的独特
Its first uniqueness is
它第一个独特就是
it was in 2015
它在2015年
concentration of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
大气里面耳熬化碳的浓度
everyone can see
大家可以看到
Here is February 2015
这边就是2015年2月
The following is 14
下面就是14
The next step is 13
再下来就是13
That is, it is February every year
也就是这是每一年的2月
everyone can see
大家可以看到
most importantly
最重要的就是
how much it rises every year
它每一年上升的幅度
about two to three units
大概是两到三个单位
Then in 2015 it has several characteristics
那2015年它有几个特征
the first is
第一个就是
It is the concentration of carbon dioxide in the air
它耳熬化碳的在空气里面的浓度
Has broken through 400 units
已经突破了400个单位
For the first time in 3 million years
这是300万年以来的第一次
it not only says
它不但是说
Breaking through 400 units this month
这一个月突破了400个单位
In fact, there are a total of 8 months in 2015
其实2015年一共有8个月
Both broke through our 400 units
都突破了我们这个400个单位
This is our past human history
这是我们过去人类历史
not available in the market
市场没有的
We just saw February March
刚刚我们看到2月 3月
it's april
这是4月
then may june
然后5月 6月
Then the next thing is
然后接下来就是
it's july november december
这是7月 11月 12月
So you can see here a series of
所以大家可以看到这边一系列的
all told us
都告诉我们说
8 months of the year break through
一年中间有8个月都突破
This carbon dioxide has exceeded 400 units
这个二氧化碳都突破400个单位
this is very unique
这个是非常独特的
Then we are all a witness to history
那我们都是历史的一个见证
This is the first anomaly indicator
这是第一个异常的指标
The second indicator is just said
第二个指标就是刚刚说的
2015 is actually the year we started in 1850
2015年其实是我们从1850年
A very accurate measure of the temperature dependence of the Earth's surface
很准确的量地表的温度以来
It has the highest global temperature
它的全球的温度是最高的
As you can see, this is the year
大家看到这边就是年度
from 1850
从1850年
this is the temperature
这是温度
temperature is the outlier
温度是用异常值
Its baseline is the average from 1961 to 1990
它的基准值是1961年到1990的平均值
We can see that
我们可以看到
It is probably the highest after this time
大概在这个时间后面都是最高的
It's just that 2015 was the hottest year since Dominance
只是2015年是优势以来最热的这一年
This is the second indicator
这是第二个指标
the third is
第三个就是
on the east side of our Pacific Ocean
正在我们太平洋的东边
There is also a sound phenomenon
还有一个声音现象
The sound phenomenon is to the east of the Pacific Ocean
声音现象就是太平洋东边
The temperature of sea water is very high
海水的温度特别的高
This time the sound phenomenon is caused by
这一次的声音现象是由
Since 1950, we have actually been since the 20th century
我们从1950年其实是20世纪以来
The strongest sound phenomenon we have ever observed
我们所观测声音现象最强的一次
This time not only the temperature of our ocean is very hot
这一次不但是我们海洋的温度非常的热
It affects all our atmospheres
它连带影响我们所有的大气
and the interaction between the atmosphere and the ocean
以及大气跟海洋之间的互动
also affects a climate on all of Earth's
也影响了所有地球上面的一个气候
This sound phenomenon so far
这个声音现象到目前为止
still in development
还是在持续发展中
It will make our climate this year come
它会让我们今年的气候来
Will bring some variables that we can't imagine
会带来我们想象不到的一些变数
Below you see the green
下面大家看到绿色的
Blue is anti-sound phenomenon
蓝色的就是反声音现象
Then this time after the sound ends
接着这一次声音结束以后
We'll be ready for the next backlash
我们就会迎接下一次的反声音
This is the third indicator
这是第三个指标
The fourth indicator we just got from the atmosphere
第四个指标我们刚刚是从大气
then into the ocean
然后进到海洋
it's still ocean
这还是海洋的
The fourth indicator is the global sea level
第四个指标是讲全球的海平面
Global sea level since 1993 we started
全球的海平面从1993年我们开始
MSI is a very accurate measure of the average height of sea level on our planet's surface
微星非常准确的量我们地球表面海平面的平均高度
We can see from 1993 to October 16, 2015
我们就可以看到从1993年一直到2015年的10月16号
that's the last bit
就是最后这一点
then throw up
然后会扔起来
Our sea levels have risen by more than 8 centimeters
我们的海平面已经上升了超过了8公分
in such a short time
在这么短的时间
Over 20 years, our sea level will increase by 8 cm
20多年以来我们海平面会增加8公分
Probably the entire past twentieth century
大概是过去二十世纪整个
double in a century
一个世纪以来的两倍
so this is a very high number
所以这是一个非常高的数字
But everyone can see
可是大家可以看得到
The last curve is still accelerating
最后的这个曲线它还在加速中
it means
它代表的意思就是
In the future, the sea level will continue to rise
未来的海平面它还会继续上升
and it will be faster
而且还会更快速
This is the fourth very unusual indicator we see
这是我们看到的第四个非常异常的一个指标
The fifth is actually very far away from us
第五个其实距离我们非常的遥远
This is the origin of this Arctic Oscillation
也就是这一次北极震荡它的起源地
is our arctic ocean
就是我们的北冰洋
The Arctic Ocean in March last year
北冰洋在去年的3月
Here's an indicator of what we saw in mid-March last year
这是去年的3月中旬所看到的一个指标
Its ice cap area is the white part
它的冰盖面积就是白色的部分
Only 14 million square kilometers
只有1400万平方公里
This is us from 1979
这是我们从1979年开始
The lowest record since the start of measurement
開始量測以來最低的紀錄
In 1979 we measured here
1979年我們量測是在這裡
We can see it slowly slide all the way down
我們就可以看到它一路就慢慢的下滑
it's winter
這是冬天
Winter is the largest location of Arctic Sun
冬天是北冰陽最大的一個位置
There are more than 1000 square kilometers
有1000多平方公里
But March 2015 was the lowest since Dominance
不過2015年3月是優勢以來最低的
only 14 million
只有1400萬
In the past you can see more than 16 million
過去你可以看到都超過1600萬
Such a phenomenon is expressed by saying that
這樣子的一個現象表示出來是說
When its winter ice cover becomes smaller
當它的冬天冰蓋面積變比較小的時候
its summer will be more serious
它的夏天會更嚴重
I will use the data to make a report with you
我會再用數據跟大家做一個報告
These five indicators all tell us that
這五個指標都告訴我們說
2015 was a very unique year
2015年是一個非常獨特的一年
this unique year
這個獨特的一年
From our atmosphere to our oceans
從我們的大氣到我們的海洋
to this far edge of ours
到我們遙遠的這個邊緣
all told us
都告訴我們說
The earth has happened a lot and there is no way
地球發生了很多沒有辦法
Things I didn't see before
過去沒有看到的這些事情
these things can happen
這些事情能夠發生
Mainly because we changed
主要就是因為我們改變了
Some important factors in our earth
我們地球裡面的一些重要的一些因素
One factor is the greenhouse gases in our large estates
其中一個因素就是我們大地產裡面的溫室氣體
we can use carbon dioxide
我們可以用二氧化碳
Its concentration is an indicator
它的濃度的高低做一個指標
Mainly look at
主要来看
This is our earth's distant past
这是我们的地球遥远的过去
Our present is at the last point
我们的现在是在最后这一个点
We look at the past 100,000 years
我们看过去的十万年
two hundred thousand years
二十万年
three hundred thousand years
三十万年
four hundred thousand years
四十万年
The concentration of carbon dioxide in our atmosphere
我们的大气里面二氧化碳浓度
it rises and falls naturally
它会自然的上下起伏
it will be high
它会高
it will be low
它会低
it will be more
它会多
it will be less
它会少
It's like the coat of our earth
它像我们地球的外衣一样
but it's more
但是它再多再多
it also has an upper limit
它也有一个上限
The upper limit is about 300 units
这个上限大概是在300个单位
it's the lowest
它最低最低
about 180
大概是在180
That is to say, they differ from each other
也就是说它们相差上下
About 100 units
大概就是100个单位左右
As long as the 100 units change
只要这100个单位的改变
the climate of our planet
就把我们地球的气候
From Warm Ages to Ice Ages
从暖期到冰期
Or from the ice age and back to the warm period
或者从冰期再回到暖期
So only need to change 100 units
所以只需要改变100个单位
The climate of our planet will be completely changed
我们地球的气候就完全截然的改观
But now our human influence
可是现在我们人类的影响
It's the blue line at the back
就是后面这个蓝色这条线
This line we amplify it
这条线我们把它放大
This is the line you see above
就是大家看到的上面这条线
We've been real since 1958
我们从1958年真实的
The CO2 concentration in the air has been so low until now
在空气中凉二氧化碳浓度一直到现在
when we only see one thing
我们只看到一件事时
It's in our atmosphere
就是我们大气里面
us
我们
The concentration of breathed carbon dioxide is constantly increasing
呼吸的二氧化碳它的濃度一直不斷的在增加
to this year's
到了今年的這個
Either this year or last July
不是今年就是去年的7月的時候
Has broken through 400 units
已經突破了400個單位
It is also the highest ever
而也是是以來最高的
The annual average for 2015
那2015年的年平均值
It will also break through 400 units
也是會突破400個單位
But it keeps going up
可是它還在繼續的上升
You can see the one we just released
大家可以看到剛剛我們放的那個
This indicator for each month
每一個月的這個指標
its annual growth rate
它每一年的增加率
It is a big increase of 2 to 3 units compared with last year
就是跟去年大增加2到3個單位
According to a rate like this
按照這樣子的一個數率
if we don't make any changes
如果我們不做任何改變的話
it will be before 2038
它會在2038年以前
will break through a very important critical point
就會突破一個很重要的臨界點
called 450 units
叫做450個單位
Once the 450 orders break through,
這450單一旦突破了以後
Our planet will bring unimaginable results
我們地球會帶來想像不到的結果
Our temperature will rise very fast
我們的溫度上升了會非常的快
The change we face
我們所面臨的這個改變
It's all beyond our imagination
都是我們過去想像不到的
So we human beings in such a
所以我們人類在這樣子的一個
Under the circumstances we made two mistakes
環境之下我們犯了兩個錯誤
The first mistake is
第一個錯誤就是
We broke a natural ceiling
我們突破了一個自然的上限
And break through very fast
而且突破得非常的快
From 200 to 300 in the past
過去從200到300
it only increases by 100 units
它只增加100個單位
Earth is from an ice banner
地球就是從一個冰旗
You flipped all of a sudden to a very warm ice age
你一下子翻转到一个非常暖的煎冰期
it only takes 100 units
它只需要100个单位
We have now added another 100 units
我们现在又增加了100个单位
You can see us from 300 before the industrial revolution
你可以看到我们从300在工业革命之前
278 We've reached 400 units now
278我们现在已经到了400个单位了
So we added 100 units in a very short time
所以我们在非常短的时间增加了100单位
So we're not only breaking a natural upper limit
所以我们不但是突破了一个自然的上限
And we increase the number rate 100 times that of nature
而且我们增加的数率是自然界的100倍
We used to go from 200 to 300 and it took us 20,000 years
我们过去要从200加到300我们要花2万年
It takes 20,000 years to naturally increase
花2万年的时间自然还可以增加
Now we only spent 200+ years
现在我们只花了200多年
So we use the data rate of nature at a very fast speed in the slave
所以我们是把自然界的数率用非常快的速度在奴隶的
This disturbs the ecosystem of our entire planet.
这样子就干扰了我们整个地球的生态系统
That is what we are facing today
也就是我们今天所面临的许许多多
Some changes we haven't seen, thought, or heard of in the past
我们过去没有看过没有想过没有听过的一些变化
In this picture, it tells us that
在这张图上面就告诉我们说
The mistakes we made were very, very horrific
我们翻的错误是非常非常的可怕
also very stupid
也非常的愚蠢
The left is a natural state
左边就是一个自然状态
this is our earth
这是我们的地球
we have a very important atmosphere
我们有个非常重要的大气层
It has very precise concentrations of greenhouse gases
它有非常精准的温室气体的浓度
The CO2 is one of the guards with this
在二氧化碳是用这个保安们之一
Oxygen Nitric Oxide, the first pill, is measured with a concentration of one part per billion
氧化氧氮這個甲丸都是用十億分之一的濃度去衡量
In the past, its changes were very limited.
那過去它的變化很有限
And it goes up and down within a very limited range
而且它是在一個很有限的範圍裡面去上下起伏
It holds the sun to our surface
它把太陽扶著到我們地表
Heat energy can be intercepted at our surface
熱能可以攔截在我們的地表
warm the earth
讓地表可以溫暖起來
but not too hot
但是不會太熱
Then it's going to decrease a little
然後它是要減少一點
It emits a little more heat
它出去的熱能多一點
our earth will be cold
我們地球會冷
but not too cold
但是也不會太冷
But now everything has changed
可是現在一切都改變了
that's what we are now
那這就是我們現在
Because after two hundred years of influence
因為經過了兩百多年影響
Our pan-nitrogen oxide
我們的氧化氾氮
Pill A and Oxygen Nitric Oxide both increased significantly
甲丸跟氧化氧氮都大幅度的增加
The rate of increase is very fast
增加的速率非常的快
It is a hundred times that of nature in the past
是過去自然界的一百倍
and it increases the amount
而且它增加的量
also surpassed our past
也超過了我們過去
This undulating quality between ice cream and ice cream
冰淇淋跟結冰淇淋之間的這種起伏的質
Now we hold the sun up to
現在我們把太陽扶著到
Our surface traps very, very much heat
我們地表的熱能攔截得非常非常多
So the thermal energy temperature of our surface
所以我們地表的熱能溫度
I watched it never go up
都看著它一直不得上升
Not only does it mean that the heat coming in from the outside cannot go out
不但是說外面進來的熱能出不去
The endotype of the earth inside us is actually a temperature exceeding
我們裡面地球的內型其實是溫度超過
Humidity 6000 degrees
涉溼六千度
It actually used to go through this long distance
它其實過去都是透過這個長途的
From the cold in the sky to the crust
从天上的地寒到地壳
and then radiate through the thick layer into our outer space
然后再透过大体层辐射到我们的外太空
now it can't get out
现在它也出不去了
So now we actually have two incoming thermal energies
所以我们现在其实有两个进来的热能
one is from outside
一个是从外面来的
we keep it
我们把它留下来
One was supposed to go out from inside
一个是从里面本来要出去的
can't go out now
现在也出不去的
stay on the surface of our crust
都停留在我们地壳的表面
So now our greenhouse gas
所以现在我们温室气体
The amount of heat accumulated on our surface is staggering
所累积在我们地表的热能是非常惊人
How amazing is it?
到底有多惊人呢
Later we have the actual data
待会我们有实际上的数据
This is what we have on the surface of the Earth today
这就是我们今天在地球的表面
all the way to the sea and all the way to our land
一直到海洋一直到我们陆地
what we observed
我们所观测的
There are 10 indicators on this
这上面有10个指标
In these 10 indicators
这10个指标里面
7 all told us that
7个都是告诉我们说
Our temperature is increasing
我们的温度都在增加
one is the temperature of the atmosphere
一个是大气的温度
One is the humidity of the atmosphere
一个是大气的湿度
One is the sea surface temperature
一个是海面上的温度
sea ​​surface temperature
海水表面的温度
heat in the ocean
海洋里面的热能
Plus the temperature of our land is also increasing
再加上我们陆地的温度也在增加
So we are now from air to sea to land
所以我们现在是从公气到海洋到陆地
that's even scarier
那更可怕的是
Our sea level increases with temperature
我们的海平面随着温度增加
it will expand
它会热膨胀
And our mountain glaciers
还有我们的高山的冰川
melting all the time
一直不断的消融
it comes in
它进来
it flows into the waters of our ocean basins
它流到我们海盆的水
always rising
一直解解的升高
So we just saw that there is a fourth indicator that is sea level
所以我们刚刚才会看到有第四个指标是海平面
rising faster and faster
上升的越来越快
that helps us regulate the temperature
那帮助我们调节温度的
In addition to the high mountain and the two-level edge
除了有高山跟两级的边缘
and snow
还有下雪
and the beach inside
还有里面的海滨
It is like our earth's natural freezer
它就像我们地球的天然的冷冻库一样
But their numbers are decreasing
可是它们的量在减少
Their functions are also slowly shrinking
它们的功能也在慢慢的萎缩
The impact on us will be more and more
给我们带来的冲击就会越来越多
So we look at these indicators
所以我们从这些指标看
like what
就像什么呢
like we did a physical today
就像我们今天做身体检查
We failed all the indicators
我们所有的指标都不及格
our snow duck
我们的雪鸭
our snow hall
我们的雪堂
our cholesterol
我们的胆固醇
We're failing every measure of our health
我们各项的健康指标都不及格
That's what we're facing on Earth today
那就是我们今天地球所面临的情况
This is the IPCC
这是IPCC
It's the Intergovernmental Commission on Changing the Name of the Post-7th Generation
就是政府间七后变号委员会
it was in 2013 to 2014
它在2013年到2014年
It released two pictures in the fifth post-Qi commentary report
它公布了第五次七后评论报告里面的两张图
we'll just put it here
我们就把它放在这边
tell everyone
告诉大家说
Because we accumulated so much heat
因为我们累积了这么多热难
Now we do scientific observations
现在我们做科学观测
we saw the unfortunate truth
我们看到了一个很不幸的事实
That is, the temperature of our surface continues to rise
就是我们地表的温度不断的上升
This is from 1850 until
这是从1850年一直到
it's 2012
它这是到2012年
From 1850 to 2012
从1850年到2012年
we can see a fact
我们可以看到一件事实
is the rate at which our entire planet's surface rises
就是我们整个地球表面上升的幅度
probably once
大概已经是一度了
This is the first one
这是第一个
In the past, the earth would rise by one degree
过去地球要上升一度
It drops by one degree, in fact, it will adjust itself
它下降一度其实它自己会调节
but it goes up one degree
可是它要上升一度
it better take 5000+ years
它最好花5000年以上的时间
We only spent 150 years now
我们现在只花了150年
So we not only say
所以我们不但是说
increase the amount of greenhouse gas accumulation very much
把温室气体累积的量增加得非常多
Our woods are growing very fast
我们树林增加非常快
We've also seen our temperatures rise
我们也看到我们的温度上升了
also very amazing
也非常的惊人
Even more terrifying is the picture below
更可怕的是下面这张图
This picture is the temperature of 10 years
这张图它是把10年的温度
do an average
做一个平均
so you see a square
所以你看到一个方块
is the average temperature every 10 years
就是每10年的平均温度
its black part
它的黑色的部分
It is the average value in the past 10 years
就是它这10年里面的平均值
past we see
过去我们看
Cubes with mean temperature per 10 years
每10年平均温度的方块
it will all overlap
它都会重叠
It goes up and down very slowly
它的上下起伏都是非常缓慢的
But since 1980
可是从1980年以后
We've seen the situation change completely.
我们就看到这个情况完全改观了
Since 1980
从1980年以后
we can see the temperature
我们可以看到温度
Every 10 years is a bouncing rock
每10年都是跳摇式的
it will never again
它从此以后不会再
Relatively together, they will not overlap
相對在一起也不會重合了
So what does this jumping up signify?
那這種跳躍式上升表示什麼呢
means that our temperature is not only rising
表示我們的溫度不但上升
And the rise is accelerating
而且上升的正在加速
This is what we are facing now
這就是我們現在正在面臨的情況
So our temperature is still increasing
所以我們的溫度還在增加
Our rate of temperature increase is accelerating
我們的溫度增加速率還正在加速
This is what we observe now
這就是我們現在觀測的結果
Next, we are not only talking about our past
接下來我們不但是說看我們過去
we can see our future too
我們也可以看到我們的未來
This is what the IPCC stated in its Fifth Assessment Report
這就是IPCC在第五次評估報告裡面的
another picture
另外一張圖
it allows us to see us now
它讓我們看到我們現在
our past and our future
我們的過去跟我們的未來
Our past is what we just said
我們的過去就是剛剛我們所說的
This is from 1950 to our present
這是從1950年一直到我們現在
We see that the temperature keeps rising
我們就看到溫度接接上升
So we in this generation
所以我們在這一代
in the process of our growing up
我們長大的過程裡面
We are all witnesses of history
我們都是歷史的見證
We've all seen this temperature keep rising
我們都看到這個溫度一直不斷的上升
But we look from now to the future
但是我們從現在往未來去看
we only see one fact
我們只看到一件事實
No matter what kind of energy reduction and carbon reduction we adopt
我們不管是採取什麼樣的一個減能減碳
or do this temperance work
或者是做這個節制的工作
Here, of course, the IPCC has made four different
在這邊當然IPCC它做了四個不一樣的
This scenario simulates
這個情境模擬
What we want most is of course this
我們最希望的當然是這個
just please blue
就是請藍色
Then there is a strong energy reduction and carbon reduction
然後是強力減能減碳
It keeps our temperature going up
它讓我們的溫度還會上升
just be slow
只是會緩慢
But others, no matter whether it is low-medium or high-medium
但是其他的不管是中低 中高
don't even make any changes
甚至於不做任何改變
It will be even more astonishing as our temperature rises
我們的溫度上升了就會更驚人
This picture only tells us one thing
這張圖它只告訴我們一件事情
We do any energy reduction and carbon reduction
我們做任何的減能減碳
well done we still have to go up
做得好我們還是要上升
It's just that the rise is less and the rise is slower
只是上升的少 上升的比較慢
we didn't do well
我們做得不好
Our future temperature rise
我們將來的溫度的上升量
it will be very very amazing
就會非常非常的驚人
In other words, our future
也就是說其實我們的未來
at least before 2000
至少在2000年之前
what we can't change
我們不能改變的是什麼
Can not be changed is the temperature will not rise
不能改變是溫度不會上升
temperature will continue to rise
溫度還會繼續上升
only through our efforts
只是會透過我們的努力
will slow down the rate of rise
會讓這個上升的幅度慢一點
it hit us less
它給我們的衝擊小一點
if we don't make any changes
如果我們不做任何的改變
Then the impact we bring will be very, very large.
那我們帶來的衝擊就會非常非常的大
Where are the shocks?
那這些衝擊在哪裡呢
That's what I'm going to tell you
就是下面我要跟大家講過的
Speaking of which means we used to go
講到就是說我們過去
Because the temperature has risen by one degree like this
因為溫度上升了這樣子的一度
what we are facing
我們所面臨的
If we continue to rise in the future
如果未来我们要继续上升
at least once
至少一度
or one and a half
或者是一度半
or more than two
或者是两度以上的话
Our increased exposure to shocks
我们所增加的面临的冲击
probably far more than
可能都远远超过
our imagination today
我们今天大家的想象
This is when the IBCD was in 2014
这是IBCD在2014年的时候
It reports a picture inside
它报告里面放的一张图
This picture is very important
这张图非常的重要
where does it matter
它重要在哪里了
What we just showed you is an indicator of temperature.
我们刚刚给大家看到的都是温度的指标
It is an indicator of thermal energy
它这个是热能的指标
Its heat energy unit is amazing
它这个热能的单位非常的惊人
One unit is the 10-21 power glue ear
是一个单位就是10-21次方胶耳
how big is this
这个有多大
I will show you an indicator
我用一个指标给大家看
In 2011, a
2011年日本发生了一个
A Great Earthquake Off the Northeast Sea
东北外海的一个大地震
long-standing
规模悠久
It was the strongest earthquake of its kind ever recorded in Japan
这是日本有史以来最强的一类地震
Bring to our earth and Japan
给我们这个地球跟日本带来
very serious injury
非常严重的伤害
The energy released by the earthquake
那个地震所释放出来的能量
About 10-18 power glue ear
大概是10-18次方胶耳
So such a unit is 1000 times its
所以这么一个单位就是它的1000倍
so you can know say
所以你就可以知道说
This is a very amazing surface energy
这个是非常惊人的一个地表能量
We are now from 1970
我们现在是从1970年
There is a more accurate measurement of this
有比较准确的这个量测
We express the result of our cool color in terms of heat energy
我们把我们凉色的结果用热能来表示
we see a result
我们就看到一个结果
From 1970 until now
从1970年一直到现在
The amount of heat we accumulate on the surface is actually very, very amazing
我们在地表上累积的热能其实非常非常的惊人
Where are these heats born?
这些热能出生在什么地方呢
born in our ocean
出生在我们的海洋里面
So the light blue you see
所以大家看到的浅蓝色的
It is our shallow city sea water
就是我们的浅城海水
The deep blue is the sea water of Shencheng
深蓝色的是深城海水
This accounts for about 90%
这个占了大概有90%
Next are the ice cities of the mountains and the polar glaciers
接下来的是高山跟两极的冰原的冰城
about 5%
大概有5%
What's left is the crust
剩下来的还有地壳
none of us thought to say
我们都没有想到说
Inside the land we walk every day
我们每天走路的土地里面
In fact, about 5% of the heat energy is hidden
其实也藏了大概有5%的热能
is brown
就是咖啡色
The last dark purple is our atmospheric depth
最后深紫色的就是我们的大气深
Actually very few
其实非常少
less than 1%
还不到1%
But it's us today
可是就是我们今天
Seeing changes in our weather
所看到我们天气里面的变化
Next, I will tell you from a Kone face like this
接下来我就会从这样子的一个通力面告诉大家
we've been through so many years
我们经过了这么多年
We have accumulated so much heat energy on the surface of the earth
我们把这个地球表面的热能累积的这么多
now hiding in our atmosphere
现在藏在我们的大气
our oceans our crust
我们的海洋我们的地壳
What kind of impact
带来哪一些的影响
This starts from the base
这是从大基层开始
What we see is this little
我们看到的是这个小小的
very thin this one
非常薄薄的这一个
But it changed us
可是它给我们带来的改变
In fact, we are every day today
其实就是我们今天每一天
every year we experience
每一年我们都会经历的
Partyization in the grassroots
以大基层里面它的党化
In terms of the heat energy it accumulates
它所累积的热能来说的话
We only see two very obvious results
我们只看到两个非常明显的结果
the first is
第一个就是
everyone can see
大家可以看到
from the past hundred years
从过去一百多年以来
The temperature of our Earth's surface has been rising
我们的地表的温度一直补单的上升
so we can all see our
所以我们都可以看到我们的
The temperature of the earth's surface is constantly rising
地表的温度一直不断的在升高
the second
第二个
Our seasons can only change
我们的季节只能改变
And it changes in the direction of high temperature
而且是朝高温的方向改变
This picture tells us that
这张图就告诉我们说
This is one of our climate simulation models
这是我们一个做气候模拟的一个模型
This model is actually very simple
这个模型其实很简单
it tells us
它告诉我们说
Changes in our planet's surface temperature
我们地球表面温度的变化
actually very interesting
其实非常的有趣
like a standard medium curve
就像一个标准的中型曲线一样
The following is the representative temperature distribution
下面就是代表温度的分布
low temperature four temperature and high temperature
低温 四温跟高温
Generally in medium curve
一般来说在中型曲线
when the normal distribution
正常的分布的时候
The lower part will be less
低温的部分会比较少
There are not many high temperature parts
高溫的部分也不多
mostly room temperature
絕大部分都是室溫
it represents our region
它代表我們的區域
represent the length of our seasons
代表我們的季節的長短
So for most organisms on Earth
所以對於地球大部分的生物來說
We should all be at room temperature
我們都應該是在室溫裡面
But when the thermal energy of our surface increases
可是當我們地表的熱能增加的時候
This center of gravity curve will shift
這個重心曲線就會移動
it is moving to the right
它是往右邊移動
when moving to the right
往右邊移動的時候
You can see that there are two very obvious results
你可以看到有兩個非常明顯的結果
first it moves this way
第一個它往這邊移動
The low temperature part becomes less and less
低溫的部分就變得越來越少
It turns out that in this dark blue so-called low-temperature part
原來在這個深藍色的所謂低溫的部分
There are so many words we put it into points
我們把它積分的話有這麼多
Now there is only a little bit left
現在來只剩下這麼一點點
on the other hand
另外一方面
The high temperature part is getting more and more scary
高溫的部分就變得越來越可怕
The high temperature part in the past is
過去高溫的部分就是
Let's integrate it to get the yellow piece
我們把它積分起來就是黃色這一塊
Now it has become such a big piece
現在已經變成了這麼一大塊
In more serious cases, the red part appears
更嚴重的就出現了紅色的部分
this is not in the past
這是過去沒有的
The red part we call record breaking heat
紅色的部分我們叫做破記錄的高溫
So bring three results
所以帶來三個結果
The first is that cold waves are getting less and less
第一個就是寒潮越來越少
Although we just passed a
雖然說我們剛才過去了一個
The so-called overlord level cold current
所謂的霸王級寒流
But this is really going to be less and less in the future
可是這個真的是將來會越來越少
But there will be more and more hot wolves in summer
可是夏天熱狼會越來越多
And we're going to see record-breaking heat just keep coming
而且我們會看到破紀錄的高溫會一直不斷的出現
That's what we're seeing seasonally
這就是我們看到的季節性的改變
Our ten years are changing rapidly
我們一年十幾正在快速的改變
This is what is happening in Taiwan right now
這就是我們台灣現在正在發生的
The Japanese came to Taiwan from 1897
從1897年日本人來到台灣
Start helping us set up seven observatories
開始幫我們設立七項觀測站
We have an accurate record of surface observations
我們有精準地表的觀測紀錄
we can see clearly
我們就可以看得很清楚
From 1897 until last year 2015
從1897年一直到去年2015年
Our annual average temperature in Taiwan
我們每一年的平均溫度在台灣來說
just like the whole world
就是跟全球一樣
just keeps going up
就是不斷的上升
In the process of rising
這上升的過程裡面
We also see that our seasons are changing
我們也看到了我們的季節正在改變
The most obvious is summer
最明顯的就是夏天
Let's use the average temperature in July as a representative
我們用七月的溫度平均溫度做一個代表
You can see this from 1897 to the present
你可以看到這個是1897年一直到現在
The one in the middle is 1950
中間這個就是1950年
this time in 1950
1950年的這個時候
The temperature in Taiwan's summer has turned over in an instant
我們台灣的夏天的溫度一下子就翻轉過去了
From cool summer to very hot and hot
從涼爽的夏天一下子變得非常高溫熬熱
Then we saw another change
那接下来我们有看到另外一个改变
is our winter
就是我们的冬天
This winter happened in 1980
这个冬天就是发生在1980年
Just now you saw the temperature of our entire surface
就是刚刚大家看到我们整个地表的温度
This average temperature every 10 years begins to change like a jumping pill
每10年的这种平均温度就开始成跳药式的改变
We can see the temperature of this winter in Taiwan
我们就看到我们台湾的这个冬天的温度
We use January as a representative word
我们用1月做代表的话
It's a drug-like change
它就是成跳药式的改变
In the past, our winter temperature will be very cold
那过去我们冬天的温度会很冷很冷
like this time we say our temperature is low
像这一次我们说我们的温度很低
It's like the temperature we saw in 1963
好像是我们在1963年所看到的温度一样
In fact, it has been difficult to appear after 1980
实际上1980年以后已经很难出现了
Temperatures like this in the past not only often appeared
过去这样子的温度不但是常常出现
and the time will be very long
而时间会非常长
But now we're only two or three days away
但是现在我们只有两三天就过去了
And it will be less and less
而且这个情况就会越来越少
We have really entered a warm winter
我们真是已经进入到一个暖冬
Here you can see a few very unique
那这边大家可以看到有几个非常独特的
It is about 10,000 to 5,000 years in the past
就是过去差不多要1万年到5千年的时间
Our earth will naturally increase by 1 degree
我们地球才会自然的增加1度
We are now more than 100 years old and have surpassed
我们现在只有100多年就已经超过了
In Taiwan
以台湾来说
Our average temperature is about 1.4 degrees warmer
我们的平均温度是差不多升高了一点四度
Our 1998 was the warmest day in Taiwan in the past 100 years
我们的1998年是我们台湾过去100年来最暖的一天
But we'll be there soon
不过我们马上就会赶过去了
So the past few years
所以过去前面这几年
we'll see a year that breaks through 1998
我们就会看到有一年会突破的1998年
Our past hottest summers were 2007 and 2014 were the hottest
我们过去的最热的夏天就是2007跟2014年是最热的
But in the future we still have new breakthroughs
可是未来我们还有新的会突破
so our seasons are changing
所以我们的季节正在改变
To change the distribution of average temperatures we can use for the 12 months of the year
改变我们可以用一年12个月的平均温度的分布
Let me give you an example
给大家做一个例子来看
It's 12 months in a year
这是一年12个月
When the Japanese first came to Taiwan
在日本人刚刚来台湾的时候
Our 12-month seasonal distribution looks like this
我们的一年12个月季节的分布大概是这个样子
That is, January is not the hottest month in July.
就是一月一直分不到七月最热
Then slowly come down and go back to 12 months
然后慢慢降下来回到12个月
We usually use the average monthly temperature of 20 degrees as a threshold
我们通常用月均温20度当做一个门槛
We call it winter when it is lower than 20 degrees
比20度低的我们叫做冬天
Anything higher than 25 degrees is called summer
比25度高的我们叫做夏天
So judging from this indicator
所以从这样指标来看的话
You can see the past 12 months
你可以看到过去12个月
January, February and March are all winter
1月 2月 3月都是属于冬天
then this is our spring
然后这是我们春天
this is our fall
这是我们秋天
this is our summer
这是我们夏天
summer is six seven eight nine
夏天就是六七八九
This line is the 10-year average from 2006 to 2015
这条线这是2006年到2015年这10年的平均值
rising every month
每一个月都在上升
You put this increase rate every month
你把这个每一个月上升的幅度
average it out
把它平均起来
It's about our annual average temperature of 1.4 degrees.
大概就是我们年平均的温度一点 四度
but you can see clearly
可是你可以看到很清楚
It's still our winter
现在还是在我们冬天的
only december january february march
只剩下12月 1月 2月 3月
Already starting to get into this not-winter range
已经开始进入这个不是冬天的范围了
But our summer is long
可是我们夏天变得很长
Then our summer temperature also increases very fast
然后我们夏天的温度也增加得非常的快
this is our present
这是我们的现在
If we follow what the IPCC told us just now
如果说我们按照刚刚那个IPCC告诉我们的
The temperature ahead of us will continue to increase
我们前面的温度还会继续增加
According to our current estimate
按照我们现在的估计
We are in the next less than 90 years
我们在未来这个90年不到的时间里面
Our temperature in Taiwan will of course increase
我们台湾的温度当然还会增加
3 degrees the change we bring will be more serious
3度我们带来的改变就会更严重
the change of season
那这个季节的改变
Let's use Taipei City as an example
我们用台北市当做一个例子
I can tell you why it is not cold in winter
可以告诉大家说冬天怎么不冷
How our summers are getting hotter
我们的夏天怎么变得更热
not cold in winter
冬天的不冷
The cold measurement of our temperature in Taipei City is very accurate
我们在台北市它这个温度的这个凉测很精准
Each hour has an observation
每一个小时都有一个观测值
we were in 1976
我们在1976年
Before 1976 to see
1976年以前去看
The temperature is less than ten degrees of the facility
温度小于设施十度的
like this time
就像这一次一样
Our temperature in the facility is ten degrees less than the facility
设施我们的温度是小于设施十度
almost fully conductive
而几乎是全导性的
we call cold snap
我们叫做寒流
You see this pair of weather bureaus
你看到这双气象局
It must have had a continental cold air mass to clean it
它一定有一个大陆冷气团来清洗
about thirteen degrees
大概是在十三度左右
Strong Continental Cold Air Mass
强烈大陆冷气团
About eleven degrees, twelve degrees
大概就是十一度 十二度
This is called a strong continental cold air mass
这叫做强烈大陆冷气团
Ten degrees less than the facility
小于设施十度
we call it cold
我们就叫做寒流
by cold standards
以寒流的标准来说
It can be less than the total hours of ten degrees of the facility in a year
一年它可以小于设施十度的总时数
Before 1976
在1976年以前
There are 167 hours in a year
一年有167个小时
has now slowly declined
现在已经慢慢下降
not slowly falling
不是慢慢下降
very fast descent
很快速的下降
From 167 to 2000
从167到2000年
Between 1976 and 55 remaining
跟1976年之间剩下55
Now only 37 are left
现在只剩下37
How many hours do we have in 2015
2015年我们有多少个小时
is ten degrees less than the facility
是小于设施十度
Many people are hard to guess
很多人大家很难猜
One hour
一个小时
This year has certainly broken through
今年当然已经突破了
But it won't exceed this number
不过也不会超过这桿数字
so you can know say
所以你可以知道说
Our winter is really getting colder
我们的冬天真的越来越不冷
According to this estimate
按照这样子的估计
We are around 2030
我们大概在2030年
before we can see
以前我们就可以看到
It may be 10 degrees in the regional facilities
可能在地域设施10度了
But on the other hand, we look at the high temperature
但另外一方面我们看这个高温
For high temperature, we say that the daily average temperature will be 30 degrees higher than that of the facility
高温我们就说日平均温度会高于设施30度
If the average temperature of your day is 30 degrees
当你这个一天的温度都平均30度的话
It's very hot at noon
就是中午的时间就非常热
about 35 degrees
大概是35度左右
For such a number of days
以这样子的日数来说
Before 1976, Taipei City probably had less than 12 days a year
在1976年以前台北市大概一年不到12天
That's an average of 11 days
就是平均是11天
Later increased to one month
后来升高到了一个月
it's a month and a half now
现在是一个半月
How many days have we passed in 2015?
我们过去2015年是多少天呢
67 days
67天
so you can see it's really increasing
所以你可以看到它真的是在增加
predicting the end of the century
预测到了这个世纪结束的时候
We have 90 consecutive days
我们有连续的90天
It's very, very hot
它的温度都是非常非常高
We are not talking about continuous
我们现在还没有说连续的
We are able to continue as in 2015
我们像2015年能够连续的
only about 15 days
大概只有15天
90 days in a row
以后是连续90天
So this high temperature is for us
所以这个高温是对我们来说
is a very serious threat
是一个非常严重的威胁
We use a 12-month average distribution like this
我们用这样子的12个月的平均分布
you can take a look
可以去看一下
Our current picture is what you can see
我们现在的图就是大家看到的
red line
红色这条线
this is what we have
这就是我们目前
we still have a little bit of winter
我们现在还有一点点的冬天
Then a short spring and autumn
然后短短的春天秋天
long summer
漫长的夏天
But in the future, if the temperature is like this
可是未来如果说按照这样子的气温
we assume
我们假定说
Taiwan's monthly temperatures
台湾的每个月温度
It will rise by about three degrees this century
到了这个世纪会上升大概三度
it's conservative
这是很保守的
That is to say, the world is rising
也就是说全世界在升高
double that of the past century
过去一个世纪的两倍
Our Taiwan was originally 1.4 degrees
我们台湾本来是一点四度
We estimate about three degrees
我们就估计大概是三度
For example, call it two
比如称以二
You can see the temperature of each month
你可以看到每一个月的温度
Its distribution is roughly like this
它的分布大概是这个样
must be linear
一定是线性的
But the result it brings is
可是它带来的结果是
First we don't have winter anymore
第一个我们没有冬天了
Because the threshold of winter is here
因为冬天的门槛在这边
the coldest
最冷的
January with the coldest temperature
最温度最低的一月
It's all over 20 degrees
都是超过二十度以上
but look at our summer
但是你看我们的夏天
it's very very amazing
就非常非常的惊人
We probably have almost eight or nine months of summer
我们大概有将近八九个月的夏天
so there will be no winter vacation
因此以后没有寒假
no winter
没有冬天
We only have three months of heat vacation
我们只有三个月的高温假
not only students
不但是学生
all people have to let go
所有的人都要放
Because in this three-month period
因为在这个三个月的时间里面
it's hard for us to go to work
我们很难上班上课
we only have night time
我们只有晚上的时候
Only then can we go out and do some activities secretly
才可以出去偷偷去做一点活动
this is our atmosphere
这就是我们大气
It changes the environment of our entire surface
它改变了我们整个地表的环境
it changes our seasons
它改变了我们的季节
Next we look at another
接下来我们看另外一个
We except the atmosphere
我们除了大气以外
Now the heat energy increases the most is actually in our oceans
现在热能增加最多的其实在我们海洋里面
This ocean it takes us the surface of the earth
这海洋它把我们地球表面
The people we have accumulated over the past hundred years
在过去一百多年了我们累积的人
it sucks it all in
它都把它吸进去了
and sucked in a lot
而且吸进了非常多
It's actually a buffer
它其实是一个缓冲技
it is a regulator
它是一个调节
It helps so much heat energy accumulated on our planet
它帮我们地球上所累积的这么多热能
sucked it all in
都把它吸进去了
From Shallow City to Deep City
从浅城一直到深城
Shencheng is the sea water below 700 meters
深城就是低于700公尺以下的海水
very huge
非常的庞大
it absorbs so much heat energy
它吸收了这么大的热能
In fact, its physical, chemical and biological properties
其实它的物理化学生物的性质
everything is changing
通通都在改变
even more frightening
更可怕的是
The interaction between the ocean and the atmosphere is very strong
海洋跟大气之间的交互作用非常的强
they are like two angry people
他们就像两个生气的人
Bad tempered people are the same
脾气不好的人在一起一样
So the interaction between them
所以他们之间的交互作用
become difficult for us to imagine in the past
变得我们过去很难去想象
we are more terrible
我们更可怕的是
When the temperature of the ocean and atmosphere increases
当海洋跟大气的温度增加的时候
we saw a terrible phenomenon
我们看到一个很可怕的现象
Nice words are now very, very strong
好语现在变得非常非常强
If there is this on January 9th
如果1月9号有这个
I saw that many people came to listen to the speech of Academician Liu Shaozheng.
我看很多人他都来听那个刘少正院士的演讲
He told us that under climate warming
他就告诉我们说在气候暖化之下
Taiwan's rainfall intensity has increased very, very alarmingly
台湾的降雨强度增加的非常非常惊人
this is what we are facing now
这就是我们现在正在面临的
Another typhoon has actually surpassed our past imagination
还有一个台风其实已经超过我们过去的想象
this is what we are going through now
这是我们现在正在经历的
That's what we actually tested
那这是我们实际上凉测的
This is from 1958 until now
这是从1958年一直到现在
We can see the amount of heat and cold above our cool gauge world
我们可以看到我们凉测世界上面的热寒量
This unit is scarier
这个单位更可怕
It is a 10.22 cm release gel
它是10.22公分的释放胶尔
It only tells us that red represents sea water at a depth of 2000 meters
它只告诉我们说红色代表是2000公尺深的海水
Black represents the deep sea water from 700 to 2000 meters
黑色的代表是700到2000公尺的深层的海水
So whether it is above the whole boiling water
所以不管是整个开水的上面
or deep sea water
或者是深层的海水
We only see one and its accumulated heat energy is very, very high
我们只看到一个它的累积的热能非常非常的高
The whole thing is two kilometers deep
整个都有两公里这么深
It's hard for us to imagine in the past
这是我们过去很难想象的
in such a short time
在这么短的时间
Its temperature thermal energy increases so much
它的温度热能增加了这么多
If we look at the distribution on the surface of the earth
如果我们用这个地球表面的分布来看的话
The red part is from 1959 to 2008
那红色的部分就是在1959年到2008年
How much heat energy we have accumulated during this time
这段时间我们累积的有多少热能
The redder it is, the higher the accumulated heat energy will be in terms of temperature indicators
越红的就代表累积的热能以温度的指标来说就会越高
Then look at our Taiwan
那你看看我们台湾
Our Taiwan is in a range where heat energy accumulation is very high
我们台湾就是在一个热能累积非常高的一个范围里面
Whether it's our east, west, south or north
不管是我们的东边 西边 南边 北边
The accumulation of heat energy is really very amazing
这个热能累积的真的非常非常的惊人
This is what our oceans are going through right now
这就是我们现在海洋正在经历的
The ones that can really cool down are of course very limited.
那真正会降温的当然很有限
The temperature changed by the accumulated heat energy of our ocean is very, very obvious
我们海洋它累积的热能改变的这个温度是非常非常的明显
This obviously has a very dire result in the rain
这个明显带来了非常可怕的结果就是降雨
Why are we getting so much rain now?
为什么我们现在降雨会变得这么多呢
because we changed the oceans and atmosphere
因为我们改变了海洋跟大气
its thermal energy and its temperature
它的热能跟它的温度
this is our past
这是我们的过去
The temperature of our oceans in the past was low
我们的过去海洋的温度是低的
The temperature inside our atmosphere is cool
我们的大气里面的温度是凉的
ocean temperature is low
海洋的温度低
So its ability to evaporate and shake off water vapor is actually very limited.
所以它能够蒸发甩水气其实很有限
The temperature of our atmosphere is not high
我们大气的温度不高
The temperature is not high, the water vapor it can contain is also very limited
温度不高它能够含蓉的水蒸气也很有限
So at that time our rainfall patterns were all moderate
所以在那个时候我们的降雨形态都是温和型的
But now everything has changed
可是现在一切都改变了
this is us now
这是我们现在
brought
带来的
The temperature of our oceans has been accumulating
我们的海洋的温度一直不断的在累积
The thermal energy of its surface is constantly rising
它的表面的热能不断的升高
it's been a steady stream
它一直不断的源源不绝
Send water vapor from the surface of the sea all the way to us
把水蒸汽从海水的表面一直送到我们大几成里面来
Then our big part is inside because of the temperature increase
然后我们的大几成里面因为温度增加
We just said that over the last 150 years
我们刚刚说在过去150年
The surface temperature of the atmosphere has increased by one degree
大气表面的温度已经增加了一度
This one-degree increase would put the inside of our atmosphere
这一度的增加量会让我们大气里面
how much water vapor will increase
水气会增加多少来
If we listened to Academician Liu Shaocheng last time
如果我们上次听了刘少成院士的话
He told us that the increase in water vapor is about 7%.
他就告诉我们说水气增加量大概是7%
This is when we presumably do climate research science
这就是我们大概做气候研究科学的时候
We probably generally accept the number
我们大概一般接受的数字
The evaporation of this 7% water vapor
这7%的水蒸汽的蒸发量
now in our air
现在在我们空气里面
if so much
如果说是这么多的话
How much water does it have?
它大概有多少水量呢
Let's use a unit as a metaphor for everyone
我们现在就用一个单位给大家来做一个比喻
This is the Three Gorges Dam
这是三峡水坝
The Three Gorges Dam is the largest dam on the surface of our planet
三峡水坝是我们地球表面最大的一个水坝
artificial dam
人工水坝
Its appearance is about 40 billion tons
它的出场量大概有400亿顿
40 billion tons is the total water consumption of Taiwan in two years
400亿顿就是我们台湾两年的总用水量
very amazing
非常的惊人
it has so much water if it fills it up
它如果把它蓄满的话有这么多水
so much water
那么多的水量
but we are in the atmosphere
可是我们在大气里面
because of the increased
因为增加了这一度
We increased the amount of water vapor by 7%
我们增加了7%的水蒸汽的量
How many three dams are there?
有等于多少个三下水壩呢
It's hard for many people to imagine
很多人倒很难想象
its more than twenty thousand
它超过两万个
So now there's so much water vapor
所以现在有这么多的水蒸汽
They are all flowing around in our Daji City
都在我们的大吉城里面四处流动
it just needs to have the right cover
它只要有合适的封面
suitable environment
合适的环境
it will use the way of super heavy rain
它就会用超大豪雨的方式
fell to our surface
就落到我们地表
So we can all see now
所以我们现在都可以看到
our surface
我们地表
And of course the ocean
当然也包括海洋
But the surface has the greatest impact on us humans
但是地表对我们人类的影响最大
The intensity of rainfall is increasing rapidly
都是降雨强度在急速的增加
This is a result of our observation
这就是我们观测的一个结果
this was last september
这是去年9月
This is a photo from the Associated Press on September 10
这是9月10号的美联社的一个照片
This is when Typhoon Ai Tao is on the 9th
这是爱桃台风在9号的时候
This is the week of September 9th in Japan
就是9月9号清晰日本的本周
This is in the place of Ikeyama in Kinugawa
这是在这个鬼怒川的池山那个地方
This flood situation
这个大水泛滥的情况
This torrential rain is Japan's past
这个豪雨是日本过去
A heavy rain that has never been experienced before
从来没有经历过的一个大豪雨
you can see these residents
你可以看到这些居民
are on its second floor
都是在它的二楼
waiting for this
在呼救等待这个
go rescue them
去救援他們
Why are they in heavy rain
他們為什麼會在大雨的時候
haven't escaped yet
還沒有逃離
because they don't even think
是因為他們根本不認為說
The amount of rain this time will be so strong
這次大雨的雨量會有這麼強
And then inflict such a serious injury on them
然後給他們帶來這麼嚴重的一個傷害
this is us today
這就是我們今天
every country
每一個國家
every environment
每一個環境
what happens to us all
我們都會碰到的情況
the heavy rain we had today
我們今天所碰到的好大雨
its intensity
它的強度
the shock it brings
它帶來的衝擊
None of our past experience
都不是我們過去的經驗
conceivable
可以想像的
Japan is so advanced in disaster prevention
日本對於防災這麼前進
so careful country
這麼注意的國家
will encounter this situation
都會碰到這種情況
the other places are the same
那其他的地方都是一樣的
all the same
都是一樣的情形
Our Taiwan is like this
我們的台灣也是這個樣子
Exactly from 1901 until last year
正是從1901年一直到去年
We saw
我們看到
Taiwan's temperature and rainfall
我們台灣的溫度跟雨量
A situation in which it interacts with each other
它彼此之間交互變化的一個情況
The red one is our temperature
那紅色的就是我們的溫度
temperature we can see
溫度我們可以看到
it's a long record
這是長期的紀錄
So it is a five-year Huadong average
所以它是一個五年的華動平均
what it sees is
它看到的就是
Our temperature is the same as the whole world
我們的溫度跟全世界一樣
it goes up and down
它會上下起伏
but it keeps going up
但是它一直不斷的上去
It's just that it's fun
只是它很有趣的就是
rise it will be leveled
上升它會被拉平
If it rises again, it will be leveled again
再上升又會被拉平
This flattening is the ocean
這個拉平就是海洋
Conditioning helps us buffer the consequences of
调节帮助我们做缓冲所带来的结果
But rising and leveling
可是在上升拉平
In the process of rising and leveling
在上升拉平的过程里面
We see that the relationship between temperature and rainfall
我们看到温度跟雨量之间
it has a wonderful relationship
它有一个很奇妙的关系
blue is rain
蓝色的就是雨量
before this warming
在这个暖化以前
before 1950
就是1950年以前
We see the rainfall in Taiwan
我们看到台湾的雨量
It's the blue line
就是蓝色这条线
It is parallel to the temperature
它跟温度是平行的
temperature rises slowly
温度慢慢的上升
Rainfall is also increasing
雨量也不断的增加
Its ups and downs are actually very gentle
它上下起伏其实很温和
The impact it brings is actually very limited.
它带来的这种冲击其实也很有限
It does very little harm to us
它对我们的伤害也是非常的小
But once sold out of 1950
可是一旦卖过了1950年
everything has changed
整个都改变了
we just saw that
我们刚刚看到说
seasons in taiwan
台湾的季节
The first thing to change is summer
第一个改变的是夏天
Summer has changed since 1950
夏天是从1950年开始改变的
Why did 1950 change
为什么1950年发生改变来
since the 1950s
因为1950年代
average temperature around the world
全世界的平均温度
For the first time surpassed our Medieval Nuki's online
第一次超过了我们中世纪暖岐的上线
So it brings up is a
所以它带来了是一个
very terrible change
非常可怕的改变
Rainfall in Taiwan
我们台湾的雨量
all at once from an amble
一下子就从一个缓步上升
becomes a
就变成了一个
A completely different shape from the past
跟过去完全不一样的形态
We call it like a roller coaster
我们叫做像做云霄飞车
From peak to first strand
从高峰到第一股
From the peak to the trough
带到高峰到要低谷
keeps happening repeatedly
一直反复的发生
every trough
每一次的低谷
That's where you see the green sword head
就是大家看到这个绿色的剑头地方
That is, our rainfall is relatively low
就是我们雨量比较低
That is, when there is a drought in Taiwan
也就是台湾发生干旱的时候
The first drought occurred in the mid-1960s
第一次发生干旱1960年代中期
We gave birth to the so-called Shimen Reservoir
我们催生了所谓的石门水库
The second drought was around the 1980s
第二次干旱是在1980年代的前后
Our Bandit Water Reservoir has been flushed out
我们的匪水水库就被催出来了
and then the third time
然后接下来第三次
For the fourth time we are now just passing a fifth time
第四次我们现在刚刚是经过一个第五次
but go back right away
但是马上又回去
so our drought will recur
所以我们的干旱会反复的发生
It's just that the time is getting shorter
只是时间越来越短
faster and faster
越来越快
used to be like this
过去这样子
15 years between the first and the second
第一次到第二次相隔有15年
Only 10 years left from the second to the third
第二次到第三次只剩下10年
Now we happen once in less than 10 years
现在我们是不到10年就会发生一次
on the other hand
另外一方面
The intensity of our torrential rain
我们的豪大雨的强度
is what you see above
就是大家看到的上面
It is the location with more rainfall
就是它的雨量比较多的位置
has been rising
一直不断的上升
especially after 1980
尤其是1980年以后
when its temperature rises rapidly
当它这个温度快速上升
The intensity of our rainfall is suddenly
我们的降雨强度一下子就
bouncing growth
跳摇式的成长
especially after 1990
尤其是1990年以后
We see the rainfall in our Taiwan
我们看到我们台湾的雨量
completely different from the past
跟过去完全不一样
in the past
过去这样
This has been the case for a hundred years
這一百年來的這種情況
just tell us one thing
只告訴我們一件事情
That is, the higher the temperature in Taiwan
就是我們台灣的溫度越高
The intensity of our rainfall is really increasing
我們的降雨的強度真的是越來越大
Because we will have more and more water and gas sinks
因為我們的水氣汇局會越來越多
It's hurting us more and more
給我們帶來的傷害也越來越大
But what I want to remind is this part
但是我要提醒的就是這一部分
Our temperature is now rising rapidly
我們的溫度現在正在快速的上升
Our 2015 is already the first ever
我們2015年已經是有史以來
hottest year on earth
地球表面最熱的一年
but it's still growing
但是它還在增長
So we expect to be entering
所以我們預計現在是在進入
The next wave of this upswing
下一波的這個上升期
during this rising period
在這個上升期的時候
We also expect this rainfall intensity in our future
我們也預計我們將來的這種降雨強度
will further improve
還會進一步的提高
It's just that we really can't simulate
只是我們真的沒有辦法去模擬
no way to imagine
也沒有辦法去想像
There is no way to get accurate
更沒有辦法得到準確
why
為什麼呢
Because we didn't have such a record in the past
因為我們過去沒有這樣的紀錄
Our boundary condition
我們的這個邊界條件
There is no way for us to have a very accurate
都沒有辦法讓我們有很準確的
But we can learn from the past
但是我們可以從過去這種
this extremeness of rainfall
雨量的這種極端性
you can probably imagine
可以大概去想像一下
The impact we face
我們面對的衝擊
This is after Typhoon Heber in 1996
這是從1996年赫伯颱風以後
We put every time this big typhoon
我們把每一次這個大的颱風
the torrential rain it brings
它所帶來的豪雨
its rainfall intensity
它的降雨強度
We take this 1996
我們以這個1996年
If the average value at that time is used as a benchmark
以那个时候的平均值当作一个基准的话
It also affects the area of ​​our Taiwan
它还有影响我们台湾的面积
This area is a percentage
这个面积就是百分比
So this is 20% 40% 60%
所以这是20% 40% 60%
This is 50%
这个就是50%
That is half of Taiwan
也就是一半个台湾
we see one thing
我们就看到一件事情
Now it's not just a typhoon
现在不光是台风
It's the blue dot
就是这个蓝色的点点
Or the plum rain is the red square
或者是梅雨就是红色的方块
Its rainfall intensity is increasing rapidly
它的降雨强度都在快速的增加
Just like everyone sees this direction
就像大家看到这个方向一样
it has been increasing very fast
它一直增加得非常的快
especially after 2000
尤其是2000年以后
Several typhoons we saw
我们看到的几个台风
like nali in our taipei in 2001
像2001年清晰我们台北的纳利
2008 New Lux in Clear Central
2008年清晰中部的新勒克
Morakot in southern Taiwan in 2009
2009年的台湾南部的莫拉克
and Sura 2012 affecting our whole north
以及2012年影响我们整个北部的苏拉
It's something we haven't seen before
都是我们过去没有看过的
the intensity of its rainfall
它的降雨的强度
the area of ​​damage it causes
它带来的伤害的面积
It's all beyond our imagination
都是我们过去想象不到的
But as our surface temperature accumulates,
可是随着我们地表的温度累积
We also expect that it will continue to grow
我们还会预计说它会持续不断的成长
In the case of Morakot
以莫拉克来说
When the past happened in 2009
過去在2009年發生的時候
it's on october 8 october 9 october 10
它在10月8號 10月9號 10月10號
three days
三天的時間
In Alishan, the annual rainfall
在阿里山就把一年的雨量
Take it all down
通通的把它下光了
It takes three days a year to bring it down
一年可以花三天的時間把它降光
we don't have a flood defense system
我們沒有一個防洪系統
Our row of red silk can withstand
我們的排紅色絲可以去承受
But we won't stop here
可是我們不會停在這個地方
We will definitely see a typhoon in the future
將來我們一定會看到有個颱風
It will take our year's rainfall
它會把我們一年的雨量
It took about two days or one day to bring it down.
大概兩天或者是一天就把它降光了
no matter where
不管這樣到哪裡
it's hard for us to bear
我們都很難去承受
it's raining
這是好雨
Next, let me tell you about the typhoon
接下來就是跟大家講說颱風
In 2015, we actually had a lot of typhoons
我們2015年颱風其實真的是不少
We average about 25 to 26 a year
我們平均一年大概會有25到26個
27 in 2015
2015年是27個
2014 is of course okay
2014年當然還好
2014 was relatively average
2014年是比較平均
31 in 2013
2013年是31個
no matter what
不管怎麼樣
When the temperature of sea water is getting higher and higher
當海水的溫度越來越高的時候
It is conducive to the formation of typhoons
它就有利颱風的形成
because of the typhoon
因為颱風形成
It has a fundamental constraint
它有一個基本的限制條件
The temperature of the sea water must be set above 28 degrees
海水的溫度一定要設置28度以上
But now we set it above 28 degrees
可是現在我們設置28度以上
The Influence of Southernization of Octave English
八度英文南化的影响
Its scope of influence is very wide
它影响的范围是非常的廣
and from every month
而且是从每一个月
Every year from January to December
每一年的1月到12月
like 2015
就像2015年一样
Typhoons can form every month
每一个月都可以形成台风
this typhoon
这个台风
Take 2015 as an example
以2015年当作一个例子
it tells us
它就告诉我们说
what might die in our future
我们未来可能会有什么去世来
the first number
第一个 数目多
Of course, 27 is a lot.
这27个当然是数目算是很多的
The second one is widely distributed
第二个 它分布广
You can see this is the southern sea of ​​Japan
你可以看到这是日本的南方海面
some typhoons form
有些台风的形成
just to the south of it
就是在它的南方海面
A place higher than our Taiwan
比我们台湾还要高的地方
represents the temperature of seawater
代表海水的温度
This place is already reachable
这个地方都已经可以达到
It is the threshold of the Shenzhen typhoon
它深圳台风的门槛
And its strength can be very high
还有它的强度可以非常的高
2015 was good for the Western Pacific
2015年对西太平洋来说还好
But for the Eastern Pacific
但是对东太平洋来说
is a very good example
就是一个非常好的例子
This is us from 2015
这是我们从2015年
compared with past averages
跟过去的平均子来比
Brown is average
咖啡色的就是平均子
Typhoons that should come every month
每一个月应该有的台风
2015 is gray
2015年就是灰色的
You can see that each month has
你可以看到每一个月都有
Except for two months that are relatively low
除了有两个月是比较低以外
These two months are relatively low
这两个月是比较低的
Every other month exceeds past average sub
其他每一个月都超过过去的平均子
This is one that tells us
這就是一個告訴我們說
The typhoon is really different from the past
颱風真的是跟過去不一樣了
There is another one because of this warm
還有一個它因為這個暖
You can see that this is the distribution of sea temperature around the world
大家可以看到這是全世界海溫的分布
The redder the color, the higher its temperature
顏色越紅的就代表它的溫度越高
We can see that this is on August 24th
我們可以看到這是在8月24號
From this observation from the satellite
我們從衛星的這個觀測
It can be seen that there are seven at the same time
可以看到同一個時間有七個
The seventh can be formed in both the Pacific Ocean and the Atlantic Ocean
第七樣都可以在太平洋跟大西洋形成
In the past we can see two
過去我們可以看到兩個
can see three
可以看到三個
It's not easy to see four
能夠看到四個很不容易了
But this time we can see seven
但是這一次我們可以看到七個
what does this mean
這個代表什麼
represents the warming of our oceans now
代表我們現在我們海水的暖化
The conditions for forming our typhoon have changed
已經把我們的形成颱風的條件已經改變了
not only change
不但改變
It also brings some challenges that we could not have imagined in the past
它也帶來了我們過去想像不到的一些挑戰
For example, on October 23 last year
譬如說在去年的10月23號
In this America is the east side of the Pacific Ocean
在這個美國就是太平洋的東邊
There's a typhoon near this place in Mexico
靠近墨西哥這個地方有個颱風
Called Patricksonia
叫做Patricksonia
as it approaches mexico on october 23
它在10月23號靠近墨西哥的時候
This photo was taken is what everyone sees now
拍的這個照片就是大家現在看到的
We estimate from the MSI and the observed instruments
我们从微星上面从观测的仪器上面去估计
Its wind speed can reach 325 kilometers an hour
它的风速可以一个小时325公里
Can you imagine that we can observe a typhoon
你难难想象说我们可以观测到一个台风
Each hour can reach 325 kilometers
每一个小时可以到325公里
In November 2013
在2013年11月的时候
There is a typhoon called Haiyan
有一个台风叫做海燕
His relatives in the Philippines
他亲戚菲律宾
We are already called Mount Tai
我们已经叫做摩尾台
Its wind speed is only up to 315 kilometers
它的风速只有最高是315公里
This is a typhoon that we have never seen before
这个是我们过去从来没有看过的台风
Its wind speed can reach so high
它的风速可以达到这么高
A wind speed like this
这样子的一个风速
how do we describe it
我们怎么样去形容它呢
We can use a tornado as an example
我们可以用龙卷风当做一个例子
Here's the U.S. Tornado Scale
这是美国龙卷风的分级表
Its side represents its wind speed
它这边就代表它的风速
how many kilometers per hour
每一个小时多少公里
The weakest tornado is our moderate typhoon
最弱的龙卷风就是我们的中度台风
Its wind speed is about 105-137 every hour
每一个小时它的风速大概就是105-137
It is our moderate typhoon in Taiwan that reaches this
就是我们台湾的中度台风到这个
Moderate typhoon from middle to this middle speed
中度台风从中到这个中间的这个极速
The strongest we call the disastrous tornado
最强的我们叫做灾难极的龙卷风
Its small wind speed is about 322
它一个小的风速大概就是322
this is very difficult to happen
这个是非常难以去发生
And the impact is terrible
而且带来的冲击是非常的可怕
But it's a tornado
可是这是龙卷风
What is the extent of the tornado?
龙卷风它的范围有多少
about 2 kilometers
大概是2公里
The wind speed of our typhoon is stronger than this
我们台风的风速比这个还要大
It's the equivalent of a catastrophic tornado
它就是等于一个灾难级的龙卷风
But its range is more than 150 kilometers
可是它的范围是超过150公里
so you can hardly imagine
所以你可以很难想象
We can actually accumulate energy to a point now
我们现在居然可以把能量累积到一个地步
The typhoon it caused was like a catastrophic tornado
它所造成的台风就是一个灾难型的龙卷风一样
it cleans any country anywhere
它清洗任何一个国家 任何一个地方
we really can't stop
我们真的是没有办法去阻挡
This is how our oceans are warming
这就是我们海洋正温
A difficulty we are facing now
我们现在所面临的一个难关
You can see we changed our atmosphere
你可以看到我们改变了我们的大气
our seasons have changed
我们的季节改变了
we changed our oceans
我们改变了我们的海洋
our torrential rain
我们的豪大雨
our typhoon
我们的台风
Now the form is completely different from the past
现在形态都跟过去完全不一样
what do we see next
接下来我们看到的是什么
We changed our crust again
我们又改变了我们的地壳
The energy of our crust is constantly accumulating
我们的地壳的能量一直在不断的累积
This continual accumulation has two unfortunate consequences
这不断的累积带来两个很不幸的结果
First
第一个
The moisture content of our soil is decreasing rapidly
我们土壤的湿度正在快速降低
Our drought is getting worse all over the world
我们的干旱全世界都变得会越来越严重
another one
另外一个
Our Keeneng energy accumulates rapidly
我们的科能能量快速累积
has affected the physical properties of our crust
已经影响了我们的地壳的物理性质
This is more far-reaching
这个是影响更为深远
This is the temperature we actually measured
这是我们实际上凉测的温度
This is the temperature inside the atmosphere
这是大气里面的温度
From 900 A.D. to the present
从公元九百年一直到现在
From historical data, we can observe
我们可以从历史的资料从观测
But we only see one fact
但是我们只看到一个事实
We are now from 1900 onwards
我们现在从一九零零年以后
Our temperature keeps rising
我们的温度就一直不断的上升
beyond the past
超过了过去
A journal recently said
最近有一个期刊说
Our earth should be entering the next ice age
我们地球应该是要进入下一个冰期的
But because of our human interference
但是因为我们人类的干扰
It's impossible for us to go back to the ice age now
我们现在也不可能再回到冰期的时候了
Our temperature can no longer drop
我们的温度不能够再下降了
We've now reversed up
我们现在已经反向上升了
And this rise
而这一上升
It will make the next ice age tens of thousands of years later
就会让下一个冰期要隔了好几万年以后
will come back
才会再回来
Not only does it change the temperature of our atmosphere
它不但是改变了我们大气的温度
The temperature under our ground now
现在我们地底下的温度
Just see the light blue one
就要看到浅蓝色这个
Its temperature is also rising rapidly
它的温度也在快速的上升
And it's very similar to the temperature of our atmosphere
而且跟我们大气的温度非常的类似
not only us
不但是我们这个
air temperature increases
空气温度再增加
The temperature of the soil in our atmosphere
我们大气里面土壤的温度
is also rising
也在不断的升高
When the temperature of the soil rises
当土壤的温度升高的时候
it had an unfortunate result
它带了一个很不幸的结果
Its evaporation is constantly increasing
它的蒸发作用一直不断的在增加
Once our things are heated
我们东西一加热了以后
we can see our water
我们就可以看到我们的水
will leave from the hot place
就会从高温的地方就离开
and then into a cold location
然后进入一个低温的位置
Therefore, the water vapor in our soil has been continuously reduced.
所以我们土壤里面的水蒸气就一直不断的减少
all the way from our soil to our surface
一直从我们的土壤进入到我们的地表
But to reach the surface is to enter our atmosphere
可是到了地表就是进入我们大气层
it also gets very hot
它也变得非常的热
because the atmosphere is warming
因为大气层正在暖化
So it starts from a low position on the surface
所以它就从地表的低的位置
just move to a higher position
就一直往高的位置迁移
simply put
简单的说
It's like we took a pump
我们就好像拿了一个Pump一样
keep sucking
一直不断的吸
take the moisture of the soil inside our crust
把我们地壳里面的土壤的水分
all the way down into the soil into our atmosphere
一直往土壤里面放到我们大气层
Then put it in a higher place
然后又放到高的地方
The result is the blue dot you see
结果就是大家看到的这个蓝色的点点
is the moisture in the soil
就是代表土壤里面的湿度
is constantly decreasing
就是不断的减少
This is what we are observing now
这就是我们现在在观测的一个情况
this was last november
这是在去年11月
We use satellites to see global earth
我们用卫星看全球地球
Because of the moisture content in the water and soil
因為它水裡面 土壤裡面的水分含量
The darker the color, the more coffee it represents
顏色越深越咖啡的就代表說
It has very little moisture and is in the arid category
它的水分非常的少 屬於乾旱等級
As you can see North America is fine
你可以看到 北美洲還好
South America is very serious Southern Africa
南美洲非常的嚴重 非洲的南部
Then the Middle East, Eastern Europe, Indian Red Continent
然後中東 東歐 印度赤大陸
Indochina Peninsula, Australia and the northern part of mainland China
中南半島 澳洲 以及中國大陸的北方
Like this every month there is one
這樣子每一個月都有一個
if you take a look
你去看一下的話
About half of the world's land
大概全世界有一半以上的土地
Now our soil moisture is seriously insufficient
現在我們的土壤的濕度是嚴重的不足
What does it affect? ​​It affects the production of our agriculture.
它影響什麼 影響我們農業的生產
Therefore, as the southernization continues to lead forward
所以隨著南化不斷地往前引化
its temperature keeps increasing
它的溫度不斷地增高
We only see one unfortunate outcome
我們只看到一個不幸的結果
The moisture content of our soil is getting lower and lower
我們土壤的濕度越來越低
our future agricultural production
我們將來農業的生產
it will be affected very, very badly
它受到影響會非常非常的嚴重
The other is our current earth science
另外一個就是我們現在地球科學
a subject of very lively debate
非常熱烈辯論的一個題目
Now when every international conference is held
現在每一個國際大會開的時候
We all have a Session that usually provides say
我們都有一個Session通常提供說
What now
現在呢
its energy accumulates in our crust
它的能量累積在我們的地殼
to our earth
到底對我們地球
What kind of impact does its geophysical action bring
它的地球物理作用帶來什麼樣的影響
we are now on science
我們現在在科學上面
are arguing we have no conclusions
正在爭辯我們沒有結論
we only have different opinions
我們只有不同的看法
One of the views I introduced here
其中一個看法我把它介紹在這邊
That is, when the warming
也就是說當這個暖化
When the heat energy is continuously accumulated and continuously increased
不斷地累積熱能不斷增高的時候
it stimulates our crust
它會刺激我們地殼
plate-to-plate interaction
板塊跟板塊之間的交互作用
Because the plates are expanding
因為板塊都在膨脹
So you too swell and I swell too
所以你也是膨脹 我也膨脹
The friction between them will increase
它們之間的摩擦會增加
plate when it's all expanding
板塊當它都在膨脹
When the interaction between them increases
它們之間的交互作用變多的時候
it has two unfortunate consequences
它會帶來兩個不幸的結果
One is that it squeezes stronger
一個就是它擠壓會更強
Second, when it exceeds the limit it can bear
第二個它超過它可以承受的限度的時候
It will use volcanic eruptions or earthquakes
它就會用火山噴發或者地震
This way to express this energy
這種方式來把這個能量把它抒發出去
So as the crust becomes more and more active
所以當地殼變得越來越活躍
We predict more and more earthquakes
我們預測地震會越來越多
Volcanoes will become more frequent
火山會越來越頻繁
At the same time it will grow in size
同時它的規模也會越來越大
so for now
所以現在目前為止
it's all a hypothesis
这都是一个假说
we are still verifying
我们还在验证
But in the verification process
但是在验证的过程里面
we'll look at past records
我们就会看过去的记录
And past records tell us that
而过去的记录告诉我们说
things to worry about
我们要待忧的事情
actually happening
其实正在发生
That earthquake is for us in Taiwan
那地震对我们台湾来说
Actually very very important
其实非常非常的要紧
because it hurts us a lot
因为它对我们的伤害很大
We in Taiwan have been working hard
我们台湾一直不断的努力
Find a way to do so-called earthquake prediction
想办法要做所谓的地震预测
This is what our earth is
这就是我们地球所
One third of our colleagues
我们有三分之一的同仁
a job to try to do
努力要去做的一个工作
We are all doing earthquake research
我们都是做地震的研究
that earthquake prediction
那地震预测
it does four things
它要做四件事情
First
第一个
when do earthquakes happen
地震什么时候发生
time of occurrence
叫做发生的时间
the second
第二个
where it happened
它发生在哪里
its right place
它正样的位置
how deep is it
它的深度有多少
The deeper it is the less it hurts us
越深对我们的伤害越小
The shallower it hurts us the more
越浅对我们的伤害越大
and this earthquake
还有这个地震
if it happens
它如果发生了
how big is it
它规模有多大
So we do earthquake prediction
所以我们做地震预测
Be sure to tell everyone these four things
一定要告诉大家这四件事情
time of earthquake
地震的时间
its location
它的位置
its depth
它的深度
and its size
以及它的规模
Unfortunately
很不幸的是
We have done so many years of research
我们做了这么多年的研究
I have been studying in the central government for more than 30 years
我在中央研究也三十多年了
Thirty years
三十多年
as soon as i entered
我一进去的时候
I started to participate
我就开始参与
Until now we have not broken through
一直到现在我们还没有突破
Now we can't do earthquake prediction right now
现在我们现在不能做地震预测
Of course we have a little success
我们当然虽然有一点点的成绩
But it's not up to the earthquake prediction
但是还达不到地震预测
We can't tell you these ten things
我们不能够告诉你这十件事情
So earthquake prediction so far
所以地震预测到现在为止
still an impossible task
还是一个不可能的任务
But although we can't do earthquake prediction
但是我们虽然不能做地震预测
we can do another thing
我们可以做另外一件事情
risk assessment
叫做风险评估
Earthquake risk assessment is the same as earthquake prediction
地震风险评估跟地震预测一样
Earthquake prediction is a very rigorous scientific research
地震预测是非常严谨的一个科学研究
But the earthquake risk assessment just tells us that
但地震风险评估只是告诉我们说
how dangerous is this
这个危险有多大
it's like we buy insurance
它就像我们买保险一样
100 Cars must be insured
100车子一定要买保险
not that you have to crash
不是说你一定要撞车
must have a car accident
一定要出车祸
But you must buy insurance to prevent
但是你一定会买保险去预防
in case
万一发生的时候
your damage will be reduced
你的伤害会减低
So we tell you today
所以我们今天告诉大家
In the following I want to tell you
在下面我要告诉大家的
not earthquake prediction
不是地震预测
Seismic Risk Assessment
叫做地震风险评估
It tells us that what we are facing
它告诉我们说我们现在面临的
high risk
风险高不高
Are we going to make some meaningful preparations?
我们是不是要做什么样的意义准备
what kind of test are we going to do
我们要做什么样的考考
First
第一个
Is the risk of an earthquake in Taiwan high?
我们台湾地震的风险高不高
The first thing I want to tell you is
第一个我要告诉大家的是
We are in an environment with several companies in one sector
我们是在一个板块几家的环境里面
our stakes are high
我们的风险是很高的
In 2015 we had several earthquakes
在2015年我们有几个地震发生了
They are all an environment of several tectonic plates
他们都是地壳板块几家的一个环境
These are the two major earthquakes that occurred in Nepal on April 25 and May 12, 2015
这是2015年的4月25号跟5月12号发生在尼泊尔的两个大地震
A scale 7.8
一个规模7.8
A scale 7.3
一个规模7.3
That is an earthquake with a magnitude of 8.3 that occurred off the coast of Chile on September 17
那这是9月17号发生在智利以外海的一个规模8.3的地震
It is just two plates
它就是两个板块几家
How far down this plate
这个板块往下几
Then an earthquake caused by the rupture of the earth's crust
然后地壳破裂所造成的一个地震
The other one was the massive earthquake that hit the Pakistan-Afghanistan border in October
另外一个就是在10月发生在巴基斯坦跟阿富汗边界的大地震
This is a few plates
这个就是板块几家
An unfortunate result of the Indian Ocean plate and the Eurasian plate
印度洋板块跟欧亚大陆板块几家所带来的一个不幸结果
Taiwan is
我们台湾就是
We are a Eurasian plate and the Philippine Sea plate
我们是一个欧亚大陆板块跟菲律宾海板块
An environment created by several companies on the Eurasian continental plate
跟欧亚大陆板块几家造成的一个环境
our bluefish to this
我们的蓝鱼到这个
Due to the relationship between several pressures, Henghu is shortening every year. By how much?
恒狐因为几压的关系 每一年都在缩短 缩短多少来
about eight centimeters
差不多就是八公分
In terms of the pressure of this place, how much it shortens is about five to six centimeters
那以这个地方几压来说的话 他缩短多少来 大概是五到六公分
It's the same here, about five to six centimeters per year
那这边也是一样 每一年大概就是五到六公分
So we are constantly pressing and colliding on one plate
所以我们就是在一个板块不断的几压 冲撞
one of
的一个
In an environment where energy accumulates, so we are the first. We are inherently prone to earthquakes
能量累积的环境里面 所以我们第一个 我们先天性就是一个地震容易发生
Our risk is high, it's a part of our nature
我们的风险就是很高 这是我们先天性的一个环境
Second, has the warming around us brought some impact to us?
第二个 我们周围的暖化给我们有没有带来一些冲击
It seems to be evolving in this direction
目前看起来是往这个方向去演进的
This is an article in the geophysics newsletter
这是在那个地球物理这个通讯里面的一篇文章
This is an interesting article from 2014
就是2014年这个很有趣的一篇文章
He put all earthquakes with a magnitude greater than seven or more from 1979 until March 2014
他把从1979年一直到2014年3月所有规模大于七以上的地震
He lists him all and calculates his frequency and he can see it
他都把他通通列出来 然后计算出他的频率 他可以看得出来
In the past, the frequency was about ten times a year, and then it increased to 12 times, and now it is about 17 times a year.
过去的频率一年大概十次 后来就升高到了12次 现在一年大概是在17次的
about
左右
so its frequency is changing
所以它的频率正在改变
and more and more
而且变得越来越多
faster and faster
越来越快
It's just that it can happen a lot in a year
就是一年之间它可以发生的次数非常多
and its size
还有它的规模
scale seven one scale eight its energy is to participate
规模七一规模八它的能量是参加
32 times the difference
是这个差异有32倍
32 times over here
那这边又32倍
So the difference between July 1 and September is 900
所以七一跟九是差900
That is, the frequency is 1000 times
就是频率是1000倍
so you can watch this too
所以这个你也可以看
Its energy is actually increasing
它能量其实也在增加
So we observe from this actual data
所以我们从这个实际上的数据观测里面
I have also seen the past few decades
也看到过去这几十年
The scale at which our major earthquakes occur
我们的大地震发生的规模
And its frequency is increasing
还有它的频率是在增加
Let's use another number
我们用另外一个数字好了
This is the US Geological Survey
这是美国地质调查所
It puts this all right globally
它把这个没事全球
It has the scale of what happens on the Global Seismic Network
它有全球地震网发生的规模
put it in place
把它的位置
its size lists it
它的这个规模都把它列出来
We have had this complete report since 1973
我们它是从1973年就有完整的这个报道
We take this data and throw it away
我们把这些数据把它汇扔起来
we can also see
我们也可以看到
Since 1990
从1990年以后
The number of times this major earthquake occurred in the world
全球的这个大地震发生的次数
is indeed increasing
极确是在增加
and increasing very fast
而且增加得非常快
The average year is about this position
平均一年大概是在这个位置
that's ten times that's fifteen times
就是这是十次 这是十五次
so about eleven times
所以大概是十一次
Now it's about sixteen times a year
现在一年大概就是十六次
It is actually similar to the study we saw just now.
跟刚刚我们看到那个研究其实是相近的
But the last few years have been different
可是最近这几年是不一样的
this is 2010
这是2010年
You can see that it has been more than 20 times until now
你可以看到一直到现在都已经超过20次了
This is a rare thing in the past
这是过去很难有的这个事情
But it's all happened now
但是现在都已经发生了
he told us
他告诉我们说
Yes, the conditions of our background are actually changing
是的 我们的背景的条件其实也在改变
We now have more large earthquakes and they are relatively strong.
我们现在大地震发生的是比较多 是比较强
So this is the second factor
所以这是第二个因素
Tell us our risks are not small
告诉我们我们风险来其实不小
The third is our own Taiwan
第三个就是我们台湾自己
Of course we in Taiwan have very few
我们台湾自己当然很少有
You have seen earthquakes with a magnitude of seven or more
大家看到那种规模七以上的地震
We usually scale 3, 4, 5
我们通常规模都是在3、4、5
scale 6 we'll have some disasters
规模6我们就会有一些灾害了
Scale 7 usually only happens once every 30 years
规模七通常都要30年才会有一次
But now even if it's a felt earthquake
可是现在就算是有感的地震
These earthquakes are about magnitude 3 or above
就是差不多规模3以上这些地震
The number of times every year is also different from the past
每一年的次数现在也跟过去不一样
This was before the 1999 Jiji earthquake
这是1999年集计地震发生之前
The average number of felt low earthquakes in a year is about 58
平均一年有感低震的次数大概是58
So you can see that it's probably like this
所以大家可以看到大概就是这样子
just 100 times
只是100次
it's probably in this place
它大概就是在这个地方
Its line has been deformed a bit
它这个线已经有点变形了
From 1999 to 2008
到了1999年到2008年
This is the one you see
就是大家看到的这一块
Its count has risen from 58
它的次数已经上升了从58
Jump to 407
一下跳到了407
probably in this place
大概是在这个地方
But since 2009
可是从2009年以后
You can see this one
大家可以看到就是这一块
until the previous year
一直到上一个年度
what is its average
它的平均值是多少
more than 600
600多了
So it's obvious
所以很明显的就可以看得出来
That's how it has been for more than 20 years
就是这么20多年以来
We can see the low earthquake in Taiwan
我们就可以看到我们台湾的低震
It's just that the frequency of low vibrations has increased.
就是有感低震的次数就变多了
it shakes low every time
它每一次发生低震
In fact, it is a release of energy
其实就是一个能量的释放
This means that the energy we can release
这表示说我们可以释放的能量
growing bigger and bigger
越来越多越来越大
It also means that our crust
也表示说我们地壳
In fact, the accumulated energy
其实累计的能量
Also through these low vibrations to express
也透过这些低震不断的抒发
It's just that the more energy accumulated
只是能量累计的越多
The number of times this low vibration will be expressed in the future
将来这个低震它要抒发的次数
The scale will be larger
规模也就会越大
So this is the third risk we have
所以这是第三个我们的风险
Actually it's not too small
其實已經不小了
what is the fourth
第四個是什麼呢
The fourth is that we have some relations with Japan
第四個是我們跟日本之間有一些關係
This is our plate distribution in the western Pacific
這是我們的這個西太平洋的板塊分布
This is the Philippine Sea Plate
這是菲律賓海板塊
This is the Eurasian plate
這是歐亞大陸板塊
this is our taiwan
這是我們台灣
this is japan this is philippines
這是日本 這是菲律賓
Four or three of our countries are in the Western Pacific
我們四三個國家都是在西太平洋
And both are affected by the extrusion of these two plates
而且都受到這兩個板塊的擠壓的影響
This is the Philippine Sea plate squeezing Eurasia
這是菲律賓海板塊擠壓歐亞大陸
We got Taiwan up
我們把台灣就弄起來了
Japan is like us
日本跟我們一樣
Philippine Sea plate
有菲律賓海板塊
Eurasian continental plate
有歐亞大陸板塊
but more complicated than us
但是比我們還複雜
It also has the Pacific sea plate and the North American continental plate
它還多了太平洋海板塊跟北美大陸板塊
So it's four plates pressed together
所以它是四個板塊相接擠壓
So the earthquake in Japan is stronger than ours
所以日本的地震比我們強
It does more damage than us
它造成的傷害也比我們大
about ten times as much as ours
大概是我們的十倍
We look at the past century
我們看過去一個世紀以來
There are four earthquakes in Japan that are somewhat related to us
日本有四個地震跟我們是有點相關
Which four earthquakes came
這哪四個地震來
The first is the 1896 earthquake we call Sanriku
第一個就是1896年我們叫做三陸地震
It occurs at the boundary of these two plates
它是這兩個板塊的邊界發生的
It's very strong with 8.5 on the scale
它的規模有8.5非常強
More than 20,000 people died
死亡的人數超過2萬個人
The second happened in 1923
第二個是1923年發生的
What happened in the Kanto region is called
发生在关东地区的我们叫做
Great Kanto Earthquake
关东大地震
It has a scale of 7.9
它的规模有7.9
It killed more than 140,000 people
它死亡的人数超过14万人
Because of the fire in winter
因为冬季发生了大火
The third is 1995
第三个就是1995年
happened in this place
发生在本身这个地方的
A magnitude 7.3 earthquake
规模7.3的地震
More than 6,000 people died
死亡人数超过6000多人
just a bit behind the plate
只是在板块的后面一点
The fourth is 2011
第四个就是2011年
Happened off the coast of Tohoku, Japan
发生在日本东北外海的
The so-called Great Tohoku Offshore Earthquake
所谓的东北外海大地震
scale 9
规模9
More than 27,000 people died
死亡的人数超过27000个人
also caused sea cliffs and
还引起了海峭以及
this death at national power plant
国家电厂的这个死亡
compound disaster
造成了复合型的灾害
These four earthquakes
这四个地震
What is its relationship with Taiwan?
它跟我们台湾的关系是什么呢
We can use this graph to represent
我们可以用这张图来表示
This is from 1900
这是从1900年
Earthquakes all over the world
一直到现在全球大地震
This is on a scale over 7.5
这是规模超过7.5的
It will be more and more densely distributed
它的分布就会越来越密
Then the scale is getting stronger and stronger
然后规模也越来越强
We just talked about the three earthquakes
刚刚我们讲了那三个地震
In terms of this time series
用这个时间的序列来说的话
1896,1923,1995
1896,1923,1995
These are the three earthquakes in Japan
就是这日本的三个地震
What is the relationship between these three earthquakes and our Taiwan?
这三个地震跟我们台湾的关系是什么呢
Because just these earthquakes
因为刚这些地震
when these earthquakes
在这些地震发生的时候
Then it happened in Taiwan
随后我们台湾也就发生了
large earthquake
规模气以上的大地震
And the death toll is more than 1000 people
而且死亡的人数是超过1000个人
We just saw that Japan is full of ten thousand people
我们刚刚看到日本都是万人
we are thousands
我们是千人
So we're basically one-tenth of it
所以我们基本上是它的十分之一
but for us
可是对我们来说
More than 1,000 people are considered a very serious earthquake
1000人以上已经算是非常严重的大地震
This is Meishan in 1906
这是1906年的梅山
This is the 1935 Hsinchu-Taichung Earthquake
这是1935年新竹台中大地震
We all remember the 1990s
这1990年我们大家都还记得的
GG Earthquake
GG地震
Now it has this earthquake again
现在它又发生了这个地震
2011 Great Tohoku Offshore Earthquake
2011年的东北外海大地震
scale is 9
规模是9
We see records of past history
我们看到了过去历史的记录
with experience
跟经验
Every time there is a major earthquake in Japan
每一次日本发生了大地震
after a while
隔了一段时间
we will happen
我们就会发生
about 10 years like this
像这个大概10年
This is about 11 years old
这个大概是11年
This is about 5 years
这个大概是5年
Next we want to say
接下来我们想说
Now there is another one in Japan
现在日本又发生了一个
stronger scale
规模更强
a bigger earthquake
更大的一个地震
Will there be a big earthquake in Taiwan?
我们台湾会不会发生一个大地震呢
we actually don't know
我们实际上不知道
Because we can't do earthquake prediction
因为我们不能做地震预测
but we can say
但是我们可以说
we risk a lot
我们的风险非常多
Because of past experience with this history
因為過去有這個歷史的經驗
we come now don't ignore
我們現在來就不要輕忽
So now we've told everyone
所以現在我們已經告訴大家了
we have another
我們又有一個
from our own environment
我們從我們自己的環境
Earthquakes around the world
全世界大地震
This phenomenon of oxidation that occurs
它發生的這種氧化的這種現象
our this
我們這個
An increase in earthquakes felt by oneself
自己有感地震的增加
Our relationship with Japan
我們跟日本的關係
so when will a big earthquake happen
所以什麼時候會發生一個大地震
we do not know
我們不知道
but you can see
可是你可以看到
about 10 years ago
過去大概要10年
In Japan, it absorbs shock and releases energy
日本它避震疏發能量
will be accumulated on our side in Taiwan
才會在我們台灣這邊累積
Then let's also generate a scale
然後讓我們也發生一個規模
large earthquake
氣以上的大地震
But this time only 5 years left
可是最近這一次只剩下5年
if we say yes
我們如果說是
next big earthquake
下次發生大地震
5 years too
也是5年的話
follow last time
跟著上一次的話
this is 2011
這是2011年
Then our time is actually very very close
那我們的時間其實非常非常近
that's pretty much where we are now
那幾乎就是我們現在
so we think
所以我們覺得說
Our stakes are really high
我們的風險真的是很高
Because there is such a high risk
因為有這樣子的高的風險
So we were in April last year
所以我們在去年4月的時候
our center
我們中央
published a policy proposal
就出版了一個政策建議書
Proposal on the Strategy for the Prevention and Control of Large-Scale Earthquake Disasters
叫做大規模地震災害防治策略建議書
just saw it and said
就是看到了說
Our Taiwan has recently
我們台灣在最近這一段時間
As our entire environment changes
隨著我們整個環境的改變
Our earthquake risk is increasing
我們的地震風險正在增加
We are not saying that there will be a major earthquake
我們不是說一定會發生大地震
But our risk is very high
但是我們的風險非常的大
like the plane we're on now
就像是我們現在坐的飛機
is malaysia airlines
是馬來西亞航空公司
So all our precautions
所以我們的所有的預防措施
Amount of our insurance
我們保險的額度
will be different from others
都要跟別的一般的會不一樣
So in this policy proposal
所以在這個政策建議書裡面
we specifically mentioned
我們就特別提到了
There are three important policy objectives
有三個重要的政策目標
I hope to remind the government to work in this direction
希望提醒政府要往這個方向努力
The first one, do not open the old house
第一個 老屋不要打
The second our lives to ensure
第二個 我們的生命要確保
The third function of our society cannot be stopped
第三個 我們的社會的機能不可以停
big earthquake can come
大地震可以來
But when the earthquake happened
但是大地震發生的時候
We will definitely be able to make our prevention trails
我們絕對能夠讓我們的防治步道
our life assured
我們的生命確保
The functioning of our society is sustainable
我們社會的機能能夠持續維繫
That's what we want the government to work on
這就是我們希望政府能夠努力的
so this is us
所以這就是我們
I hope everyone can also notice
希望大家也能夠去注意到的
that used to be from
那過去從
From 1901 to 2015
从1901年到2015年
There have been earthquakes of this magnitude above six in Taiwan.
台湾发生过规模六以上的这种大地震
if we draw it
我们把它画出来的话
It's the drop-down map you see
就是大家看到的直降图
All the stars represent scales over six
那所有的星星就是代表规模超过六
It will hurt us a little bit
它对我们的伤害都会有一些
impact on us
给我们带来的影响
must not be ignored
一定不可以轻忽
it is basically divided into three places
它基本上分成三个地方
One is our northeast earthquake belt
一个就是我们的东北地震带
The other one is the Western Seismic Belt
另外一个就是西部地震带
Another one is the Northeast Earthquake Belt
还有一个就是东北地震带
then we just said
那我们刚刚说
Which of these three earthquake zones is the most dangerous
这三个地震带里面哪一个最危险
That's the Western Seismic Belt, of course.
那当然是西部地震带
why
为什么呢
Because of these three big earthquakes that we just saw
因为我们刚刚看到的这三个大地震
It is mainly in our western seismic zone
它主要就是在我们的西部地震带
Taichung Miaoli in 1935 This
1935年的台中苗栗这个
And the miracle of 1999
还有1999年代的奇迹
Meishan in 1900
1900年的梅山
They are all in our western seismic zone
都是在我们西部地震带
Because the extrusion of this place is very significant
因为这个地方它的这个挤压非常的显著
But it has very few small earthquakes
但是它的小地震非常的少
We just saw 600+ oil rod quakes a year
我们刚刚看到一年有600多个油桿地震
More than three quarters are in our Northeast earthquake zone
四分之三以上都是在我们东北地震带
just let it out
就把它抒发出去了
just knock the energy out of it
就把能量把它弄掉了
But the western earthquake zone will be less fat
但是西部地震带就会肥少少
So this place is still our style
所以这个地方还是我们这个风格
most severe
最嚴重的
So everyone must not ignore
所以大家一定不要輕忽
There's one more thing we're worried about
還有一個我們覺得比較擔心的
It is the Taipei Metropolitan Area in our Northeast Earthquake Zone
就是我們東北地震帶的台北都會區
You can see we had an earthquake in the past
你可以看到我們過去曾經發生過一個地震
But in the past this was 100 years ago
但是過去這是在100年以前
It is different from our current conditions
它跟我們現在我們的條件已經不一樣
There are now more than 6 million people in Taipei City
現在台北市已經有600多萬人
Not only do we now have a large population
我們現在不但是人口眾多
we have a very important construction
我們還有非常重要的建設
our MRT our subway
我們的捷運 我們的地鐵
Our high-speed trains are all underground
我們的高鐵都是在地底下
So if an earthquake occurs in this place
所以這個地方如果發生地震
the harm done to us
對我們造成的傷害
Of course you can't ignore
當然也不可以輕忽
In addition to the earthquake on the earthquake road
除了在地震路上發生地震以外
If it happened off our northeast coast
如果它發生在我們的東北外海
This is the Okinawa Trench
這是沖繩海溝
Our southwest coast is the Manila Trench
我們的西南外海這是馬尼拉海溝
It will also have a tsunami formation
它也會有海嘯的形成
in the qing dynasty
在清朝的時候
Whether it's Kaohsiung, Tainan or Keelung
不管是高雄 台南 或者是基隆
There are records of tsunamis
都有海嘯的記錄
just tell us
就告訴我們說
There was an undersea earthquake
當時發生過海底地震
So if this time it happened in the Northeast Sea too,
因此如果這一次也發生在東北外海的話
There will also be a tsunami risk like Japan
也會像日本一樣會有海嘯的風險
This is something we must never ignore
這是我們絕對不可以輕忽的
So our northeast coast and our new South China Sea
所以我們的東北沿岸跟我們的新南海
The south coast is where we need to pay special attention
南沿海都是我们需要特别注意的地方
this is what we just saw
这就是我们刚刚看到的
From the atmosphere to the ocean
从大气到海洋
to our crust
到我们的地壳
Next, I will add one more
接下来我再跟大家补充一个
It is the edge of our mountain and the two levels
就是我们的高山跟两级的边缘
The white piece of ice dust that you see
大家看到的白色的这一块冰尘的
Its energy is also accumulating
它的能量也在累积
This accumulation affects us
这个累积给我们带来影响
actually very profound
其实非常的深远
It's actually the same as our crust
跟我们的地壳其实是一样
but its impact on us
但是它对我们的冲击
It is also what we are about to face
也是我们马上要去面临的
The first one is in this ice dust
第一个就是在这个冰尘里面
because it melts fast
因为它融化得很快
It also makes our temperature rise very, very obvious
它也让我们这个升温非常非常的明显
Its impact is in the two-level region
它所带来的冲击在两级地区
The impact on our world is very, very serious
对我们全球的影响是非常非常的严重
Even more frightening is that it not only affects the climate
更可怕的是它不但影响气候
Affecting the rise of the north face of the sea
影响海北面上升
will also affect the stability of our crust in the future
也会影响到我们未来地壳的稳定
In other words, it will indirectly affect our earthquakes
也就是间接地会影响到我们地震
volcano it's this happening
火山它的这种发生
This is from 2000 to 2009
这是从2000年到2009年
We put the whole world where the temperature is rising
我们把全世界这个温度上升的地方
make a consolidation
做一个盘整
The decade's record
这十年的记录最
The warmed place is the reddest and deepest place
暖化的地方就是最红最深的地方
We can see that there are two places
我们可以看到有两个地方
One is the Arctic
一个就是北极区
One is the Antarctic Peninsula
一个就是南极半岛
These two places are our polar regions
这两个地方都是我们的极区
It heats up not only the fastest
它升温不但是最快
At the same time, it has a great impact on us
同时它对我们造成的影响也非常的大
What I want to introduce to you today is our Arctic region
我今天给大家特别介绍的是我们的北极地区
Because the Antarctic region basically
因为南极地区基本上
It is only limited to the Antarctic Peninsula and the seven continents.
它只还极限在南极半岛跟七大陆这一块
Other places are pretty good
其他地方都还算好
Our more pressing concern is our Arctic Circle
我们比较急迫的就是我们的北极圈
This time the arctic shock
这一次的北极震荡
It spread from here
就是从这边扩散出去的
The warming of the Arctic Circle is currently the largest in the world
北极圈它的升温是全世界现在目前最大的一个地方
we talked about sea level rise
我们讲到海平面上升的话
We must mention three
我们一定要提到三个
One is the ice city above our Antarctic continent
一个就是我们南极大陆上面的冰城
very thick
非常的俱厚
One is Greenland in the Northern Hemisphere
一个就是北半球的格林兰
The roadside above it is also very anti-big
它上面的路边也非常的防大
The third is all our alpine glaciers
第三个就是我们所有的高山冰川
But all alpine glaciers
不过所有的高山冰川
you add up all its ice
你把它的冰通通加起来
Its volume is 180,000 cubic kilometers
它的体积就是18万立方公里
one cubic kilometer
一立方公里
is eleven tons of water
是十一噸的水量
The effect it can have at our sea level
它能夠在我們海平面所造成的效應
Actually not high
其實不高
probably all melted
大概全部通通融化
It's only half a meter up
也不過上升半公尺
This is measured in meters
這是以公尺做的衡量
we are more worried
我們比較擔心的
One is Greenland in the northern hemisphere
一個是北半球的格林蘭
it will take us over six meters
它會讓我們超過六公尺
The other is our entire Antarctic continent
另外一個就是我們整個的南極大陸
Antarctica you can see
南極大陸你可以看到
All add up to more than 70 meters
通通加起來就超過七十公尺
So those are the two things we're most worried about
所以這是我們最擔心的兩塊
This piece is what I want today
其中這一塊就是我要今天
I would like to introduce you to Greenland
跟大家特別介紹的格林蘭
in our northern hemisphere
就在我們的北半球
This is Antarctica
這就是南極大陸
Antarctica is the fastest-heating continent we have right now
南極大陸我們現在升溫最快的
This is the Antarctic Peninsula
就是這個南極半島
Then there's West Antarctica
然後接下來就是南極西大陸
Because the area of ​​the ice sheet on the West Antarctic Continent melts
因為南極西大陸它冰蓋的面積融化的話
would raise the sea level by eight meters
會讓海平面上升八公尺
But so far its impact
不過目前為止它的衝擊
Not so fast and obvious
還不是那麼快速跟明顯
Our biggest concern right now is Greenland
我們現在最擔心的就是格林蘭
this is greenland
這是格林蘭
this is our arctic ocean
這是我們的北冰洋
this is our arctic
這就是我們的北極區
Its impact is actually very, very serious
它帶來的影響其實是非常非常的嚴重
I just said Arctic
剛剛說了北冰
If all of this Greenland melts
這個格林蘭如果全部融化的話
Global sea levels will rise
全球的海平面會上升
Exceed
超過
6 meters
6公尺
That is to say, this piece
也就是说说就是这一块
So what is the biggest impact of this piece?
那这一块它最大的冲击是什么呢
This is the Arctic Ocean
就是这个北冰洋
Arctic Ocean due to warming
北冰洋因为暖化的关系
it's gone
它的这个消失
It melts very, very fast
它的融化变得非常非常的快
But the Arctic Ocean is a seashore
可是北冰洋它是一个海滨
Greenland is the land bank
而格林兰才是陆滨
The beach is the water in the glass
海滨就是杯子里面的水
It melts the water inside the cup does not rise
它在融化杯子里面的水不会上升
But it is a protected plant of Greenland
但是它却是格林兰的保护栽
that is, its moderation
也就是它的缓中
Without this Arctic Ocean Greenland
没有了这个北冰洋格林兰
The barrier will be lost in an instant
一下子就会失掉了屏障
it will melt quickly
它就会很快的融化
So the Arctic Ocean is where we do this climate observation
所以北冰洋是我们做这个气候观测里面
A very important observation indicator
非常重要的一个观测指标
I just said this indicator
那这个指标我刚刚已经说了
in 2015
在2015年
it used to be in winter
它曾经在冬天的时候
The area of ​​its ice sheet has become very, very small
它的这个冰盖面积变得非常非常的小
lowest since dominance
优势以来最低的
What you can see on the picture is from 1979
那在图上面大家看到的就是从1979年
Until the biggest winter of 2015
一直到2015年这个冬天最大的时候
This waterfront area we call March
我们叫做3月的这个海滨面积
It's the youngest time in summer
已经夏天最小的时候
We call the seaside area of ​​september
我们叫做9月的海滨面积
A curve of the two changes of seashore area
海滨面积它们两个变化的一个曲线
This is what we just saw
刚刚我们看到的就是这个
so-called March
就是所谓三月
the biggest winter
冬天最大的时候
Last March was the lowest in this place
在去年三月的时候是最低的在这个地方
Why should we worry so much at our lowest?
为什么在最低的时候我们要很担心呢
because in the past
因为在过去
every time its lowest
每一次它最低的时候
The last time it was 2006
在上一次的时候就是2006年
this is 2011
这是2011年
they are very low
它们都非常低
every time it's low
每一次它很低的时候
Next we summer every other summer
接下来我们夏天隔一年的夏天
Its beach area is even lower
它的海滨面积就更低
So you can see in 2006 this is 2007
所以你可以看在2006 这是2007
it's very low
它非常的低
2011 it was 2012
2011 它是2012
what is this now
现在这是什么
So we predict that by 2016
所以我们预测到了2016年的时候
Our summer waterfront area
我们的夏天的海滨面积
It will probably be lower than this
大概就会比这个还要低
2012 was the lowest
2012年是最低的一次
How much of its ice sheet remains in summer
它的冰盖面积在夏天剩下多少
3.41 million square kilometers
341万平方公里
how much in the past
过去是多少
past in this
过去在这个
before
以前的时候
In 1980 it was about the same
在1980年的时候是差不多
7.9 million
790万
Nearly 8 million square kilometers
將近800萬平方公里
Now there are only about 3 million left
現在這個只剩下300多萬
Then this year, there will be only about 4 million square kilometers left.
那今年只剩下大概是400多萬平方公里
Then next year will be this year
那明年就是今年了
This is the September we are facing now
就是我們現在要面臨的這個9月
We estimate that it will be lower than 3.41 million
我們估計大概會比341萬還要低
follow this trend
按照這個趨勢
You don't need this very accurate model like ours
你不需要像我們這個很精準的這個模型
or our simulation to predict
或者是我們的那個模擬去預測
We just use simple math
我們光用簡單的數學
we can all tell
我們都可以看得出來說
According to the trend like this
按照這樣子的趨勢
when will we see
我們什麼時候會看到
There is a summer in the Arctic Ocean without soldiers
有一個沒有兵的北冰洋的夏天出現
Of course there will be winter
冬天當然還會有
will summer appear
夏天會出現呢
From this estimate
那從這樣子的估計
Probably no more than 2030
大概不超過2030年
We are now in 2016
我們現在是2016年了
So we really don't have much time
所以我們的時間其實真的是不多
When this is before 2030
當這個2030年以前
the piece we saw
我們看到的這一塊
This is called the Arctic Ocean coast
這叫做北冰洋海濱
This was in 2012
這是在2012年的時候
Then in the future it will be smaller than this sea
那未來它會比這個海要小
then getting smaller
然後越來越小
Getting smaller and smaller
越來越小
will eventually disappear
最後就會消失
when it disappears
當它消失不見的時候
will happen
就会发生
Then I won't talk about other things today.
那我今天其他的事情就不讲了
I only talk about this matter
我只讲这件事情
That's when the Arctic Sun has no ice in the summer
就是当这个北冰阳在夏天没有冰的时候
The first to be affected was Greenland
第一个受到影响的就是格林兰
Greenland is so thick
格林兰上面的这么厚的
2.6 million tens of thousands of cubic kilometers of water
260几万立方公里的水量
will be affected
就会受到影响
It only needs to disappear 1/1
它只要消失1分之一
Our global sea level will rise by 60 cm
我们全球的海平面就要上升60公分
So the sea level will be affected by the arctic sun
所以海平面会因为北冰阳
when there is no summer
在夏天没有的时候
will start to speed up the dissolution of Greenland
就会开始让格林兰加速奔解消融
Then the global sea level will rise by leaps and bounds
然后全球的海平面就会成跳躍式的上升
This is a problem we are going to face now
这就是我们现在要去面临的一个问题
And it's not that long
而这个问题的时间其实不长
Following the trend we just looked at
按照我们刚刚看的那个趋势
We'll have to face it before 2030
在2030年以前我们就要去面对它了
This is the IPCC on a seminar
这是IPCC在一个研讨会上面
a data published by it
它公布的一个数据
it tells us
它告诉我们说
From 1900 to the present and the future
从1900年一直到现在到未来
Possible Trends in Our Global Sea Level Rise
我们全球海平面上升可能的趋势
The future is of course blue and this is history
未来当然是蓝色这是历史记录
This is the one you see
就是大家看到的这一块
this is 1900
这是1900年
until 2000
一直到2000年
The world has risen in 100 years
全球在100年的时间里面上升了
this is centimeters
这是公分
Rise about 20 cm
上升了大概是20公分
So the average year is 0.2 cm
所以平均一年是0.2公分
is 2 kilometers
就是2公里
But in the future our sea level
可是未来我们的海平面
100 years 200 years 300 years
100年200年300年
Just continue to rise in this way
就是按照这样子的方式继续上升
Its inaccuracy is our gray area
它的不准确度就是我们灰色的这一块
but now we all know
可是现在我们都知道
This estimate is too conservative
这个估计已经太保守了
not accurate anymore
已经不准确了
now we know that
现在我们知道说
before 2000
在2000年之前
It was originally estimated to be only one meter at most
原先它估计最多只有一公尺
now we find
现在我们发现
Words go so fast with our environment
随着我们环境的话得这么快
the edge of our two levels
我们的两级的边缘
it disappears so quickly
它消失得这么迅速
It has such a big impact
它带来的冲击这么的大
we now know that
我们现在知道说
Probably at least one meter
大概最少是一公尺
How many more than one meter
一公尺以上会有多少
we don't really have an answer right now
我们现在其实没有答案
we totally want to see
我们完全要看说
We can slow climate warming in the future
我们将来可以让气候暖化减缓
Then let it happen how slowly you decide
然后让它发生了有多慢来决定
But we are now one meter
但是我们现在一公尺
Probably can't escape
大概是已经逃不掉了
So now I'm going to tell you that it's unfortunate
所以现在我要告诉大家是很不幸的
before 2000
在2000年之前
we rise below
我们上升之下
one meter
一公尺
How much have we been in the past 100 years
我们过去100年是多少
20 cm
20公分
But the next 100 years is one meter
可是未来的100年是一公尺
The difference is really, really big
这个差异真的是非常非常的大
So 21st century sea level
所以21世纪海平面
rapid rise like this
这样子快速的上升
Let's face the very terrible
让我们面临了非常可怕的
We just said that the 21st century is the century of high temperature
我们刚刚说21世纪是高温的世纪
is the century of extreme change in water resources
是水资源它极端变化的世纪
It is our agricultural production that will be impacted
是我们农业生产会受到冲击的
a century of famine
一个饥荒的世纪
But when the sea level rises
可是当海平面上升的时候
it tells us
它告诉我们说
all the coasts of the world
全球所有沿海这些地方
Its population is rapidly beginning to migrate
它的人口都要迅速的开始迁移
move to higher places
到往高的地方去移动
So this is a century of great migration
所以这是一个大迁徙的世纪
The same is true of our Taiwan
我们的台湾也是一样
Mainland China has actually been hit very, very hard
中国大陆其实受到冲击是非常非常的大
So if we are going to develop in mainland China
所以如果说我们要去中国大陆发展
These are the ones to avoid in particular
以特别要避开的就是这些
places that will be hit in the future
将来会受到冲击的地方
our taiwan
我们的台湾
If we use a 3D topographic map to show it
我们用3D的地形图去把它展现的话
that's it
就是这样图
The very low place in this picture is the altitude
这张图里面非常低的地方就是海拔
Below 25 meters
低于25公尺以下的地方
all these dark blue
都是这些深蓝色的
then light blue
然后淡蓝色的地方
The gray ones are places below 100 meters above sea level
灰色的都是海拔100公尺的以下的地方
The yellow ones are places above 100 meters above sea level
黄色的就是海拔100公尺以上的地方
Above 100 meters is
100公尺以上的地方就是
When Antarctica Melts
当南极都融化的时候
we won't be drowned
我们也不会被淹没了
This is where Taiwan will always be
这是台湾永远都会在的地方
So Taiwan now we still have these dark blue locations
所以台湾现在我们还有这些深蓝色的位置
But slowly with warming
可是慢慢随着暖化
it will slowly disappear
它就会慢慢的消失
It has a huge impact on us
它对我们的冲击其实非常大
You can see that the Lanyang Plain is missing
你可以看到蓝阳平原这一块不见了
Our Taipei Basin
我们的台北盆地
many people don't know
很多人都不知道
Three-quarters of the area of ​​our Taipei land
我们台北地有四分之三的面积
All below 20 meters
都是低于20公尺
Therefore, after the sea plain rises in the future,
所以将来海平原上升以后
Along this Guandu this love mouth
沿着这个关渡这个爱口
it will slowly sink in
它就会慢慢的淹进来
our west coast
我们的西部沿海
Especially from the south of Changhua
特别是从彰化以南
until our Pingtung
一直到我们的屏东
The impact is actually very, very big
受到冲击其实非常非常大
In fact, we don't have much time for shadows
其实我们阴影的时间不多
we just said
我们刚刚说
when this arctic sun it has no ice in summer
当这个北冰阳它在夏天没有冰的时候
This phenomenon will start to become more and more serious
这个现象就会开始变得越来越严重
Then we don't have much time
那我们的时间其实不多
We are now so shadowy time
我们现在那么阴影的时间
only ten years
都还只有十几年
not more than one generation
不会超过一代
So we really need to go well
所以我们真的是需要好好的去
face the shadow
面对阴影
This is our current Taipei local
这是我们现在的台北本地
This Taipei local is now crowded with more than 6 million people
这个台北本地现在挤了600多万人
We thought we could stay in Taipei for the rest of our lives
我们以为我们可以在台北能力灯待一辈子
We can all develop assets here
我们都可以在这边资产都可以去发展
but we were all wrong
可是我们都错了
With this warming
随着这个暖化
With our rapidly changing environment
随着我们环境快速的变化
We estimate that in the next one or two hundred years, Taipei
我们估计台北在未来的一两百年
it will start to change rapidly
它就会开始急速的改变
it will make many of us
它会让我们许许多多的人
because of sea level rise
因为海平面上升
Because the water in it can't drain out
因为里面的水都排不出去
It began to make it impossible for many people to live here
开始让很多人没有办法在这边安居内
finally have to leave
最后都要离开
So the locals in Taipei actually started from this
所以台北本地其实从这个
For our earth science research
我们的地球科学研究来说
it's actually very dangerous
它其实是非常危险的
We have to migrate slowly to higher places
我们必须要往高的地方慢慢遷移
but we don't have much time
但是我们的时间真的不多
More than 6 million people
600多万人
if you want to migrate it
你要把它遷移的话
how do you migrate
你要怎么遷移
in such a short time
在这么短的时间
in such a limited time
在这么有限的时间里面
So I put just that
所以我把刚刚那个
This picture of IPCC, this energy accumulation
IPCC这张图 这张能量累积
From atmosphere to ocean to crust
从大气到海洋到地壳
until the edge of Gao Shan's two levels
一直到高善两级的边缘
tell everyone
告诉大家说
we created an unfortunate environment
我们造成了一个很不幸的环境
we made a terrible crop
我们犯了一个很可怕的作物
we hurt our earth
我们把我们的地球伤害
which in turn affects us
更反过来影响到我们
So the twenty-first century is a
所以二十一世纪是一个
post period extreme change catastrophe life time era
期后极端变化灾难平生的时代
We are now suffering a consequence of this
我们现在正在承受这样子的一个结果
This is the German debt insurance company
这是德国债保险公司
A picture he accumulated and published
他所累积跟公布的一张图
He began to report natural disasters all over the world in 1980
他从1980年开始把全世界自然灾害
accumulate it with different scales
用不同尺度的把它累积起来
We can see that this is the number of times a year
我们可以看到这是一年的次数
Average times over the past year
过去一年平均的次数
400 times at 200 times
在200次400次
about 300 times
大概是在300次
Then it went up to 500 times
后来就上升到了500次
Then received 700 times
然后接收到700次
In the past ten years
在过去的这个十年里面
It has probably risen to about 900 times
大概已经上升到了900次左右
Last year, more than 1,000 times
去年呢 超过了1000次
so we only see one result
所以我们只看到一个结果
With this global warming
随着这个地球暖化
With the increasing number of natural disasters
随着自然灾害不断的增加
Disasters we face
我们面对的灾害
In fact, more and more dangerous
其实越来越凶险
It's hurting us more and more
对我们造成的伤害越来越大
Taiwan is a natural disaster
我们台湾本来就是一个天然灾害
very big place
非常大的地方
Disasters that 73% of us face
我们有73%的人需要面对的灾害
three types of natural disasters
三種的自然災害
90% of us need to face two kinds of natural disasters
我們有90%的人需要面臨兩種自然災害
But with global warming
但是隨著全球暖化
Our ecological environment has been harmed so much
我們的生態環境受到這麼大的傷害
our risk is greater
我們的風險更大
Our challenge is higher
我們的這個挑戰更高
In the knowledge test of the previous month
在上一個月的這個知識項驗裡面
Director Lin of the Political Institute
那個 政治所的林所長
gave us the season theory
給我們講了這個賽季理論
During the season he talked about two things
賽季裡面他講到了兩件事情
That is to say, suppose there are two people
就是說假定有兩個人
Both men were caught by the police
這兩個人都被警察抓了
if they cooperate
如果他們合作的話
They will serve the shortest time in prison
他們服刑的時間會最短
They can all get the best result
他們都可以得到最好的一個結果
if they both betray each other
如果他們都背叛對方的話
both of them will be unlucky
他們兩個人都會很不幸
The season theory is not only applied to our politics
那賽季理論不但是應用在我們政治
Applied in many fields of our
應用在我們很多的領域
also applied to our climate change
也應用在我們的這個氣候變遷
Our Climate Change Now
我們的氣候變遷現在
The vice president we just said
我們剛剛那個副院長說
Just passed the Paris climate negotiations
剛剛才經過了這個巴黎氣候的談判
Climate negotiations is a very important season theory
氣候談判就是一個很重要的賽季理論
he told us
他告訴我們說
We must never again harm our environment
我們絕對不能夠再傷害我們的環境
We can no longer see ourselves like this
我們不能夠再把我們自己像這個
two people are the same
兩個人一樣
Let's do the biggest damage to each other
我們去把對方做最大的一個傷害
with torture
跟折磨
we must sacrifice ourselves
我們一定要犧牲我們自己
We would rather sacrifice ourselves first
我們寧可先犧牲我們自己
benefit each other
讓對方得到好處
Although we won't get the biggest
雖然說我們不會得到最大的
We won't get the maximum number of points ourselves
我們自己不會得到最大的點數
But the result of our joint efforts
但是我們共同大家努力的結果
will make our environment better
會讓我們的環境變得更好
this is our climate change
這就是我們的氣候變遷
One of the most important of our negotiations
我們談判的一個最重要的
That is to say
也就是說
we must first sacrifice ourselves
我們必須先犧牲我們自己
Then complete our overall situation
然後成全我們這個全局
And perfect our earth our future
而成全我們地球我們的未來
in this case
在這種情況之下
All we have to do is two very important things
我們要做的就是非常重要的兩件事情
the whole world has to do
全世界都要做
The first must be simple and simple
第一個一定要簡簡單簡單簡單
is that we just saw all these changes
就是讓我們剛剛看到所有這些變化
The first one, its change will be relatively small
第一個它的變化會比較小
it is slower
它比較緩慢
It used to be like this
過去是要這樣子的上去
now we can slowly
現在我們可以慢慢的
give us more time to deal with
讓我們有更多的時間去應應
And then let this change make us more bearable
然後讓這個變化讓我們更能夠去承受
But there is another thing I want to remind everyone
但是另外一個我要提醒大家的
What cannot be ignored is the housing debt
不可以忽視的就是這個房債
in 101 years
在101年的時候
The Executive Yuan also announced
行政院也就公佈了
National Climate Change Adaptation Policy Framework
國家氣候變遷調適政策綱領
in this program
在這個綱領裡面
In fact, the two most important points
其實最重要的就是這兩點
One is that we must start reducing energy and carbon
一個就是我們一定要開始減能減碳
to slow down
要做減緩的動作
Second, we must start to make some adjustments
第二個我們一定要開始做一些調適
The so-called adjustment is what we just said
所謂的調適就是我們剛剛說的
Be sure to start doing housing debt operations
一定要開始做房債營運
How can we reduce energy and carbon?
我們的減能減碳再怎麼做
we still need time
我們還需要時間
All countries in the world need to work hard to achieve this operation
需要全世界各國努力的去這個營運
We are now in 2016
我們現在是在2016年
right here
就是在這個地方
We emit so much carbon a year
我們一年排的碳有這麼多
If we can work together globally
如果我們全球都能夠一起努力的話
We're probably headed in this direction
我們大概就是往這個方向走
We will now line up for a year
我們現在一年會排
The total amount is about 30 billion tons of carbon dioxide
總量大概是300多億噸的二氧化碳
but we are willing to do these things
但是我們願意做這些事情
Carbon Pujo Storage Renewable Energy Nuclear Energy
碳普霍 封存 再生能源 核能
Of course we cannot use nuclear energy in Taiwan
當然我們台灣不能核能
We replace it with other
我們用其他的替換替代
We increase power generation efficiency
我們增加發電效率
Fuel Switching Energy use replace it
燃料轉換 能源使用把它替代
We even increased our debuff
我們甚至於增加我們的減能
with our efficiency
跟我們的效率
we can walk slowly from here
我們就可以慢慢從這個地方走
We hope that by 2050
我们希望在2050年的时候
The world can drop to 141 tons
全球能够降到141顿
if we can do this
如果我们能够做到这样子的话
The agricultural soil of our large strata will not break through
我们大地层的农土就不会突破
WE JUST SEE THE TERRIBLE THRESHOLD OF 450
我们刚刚看到450的可怕门槛
but we need 35 years
但是我们需要35年
In 35 years we tried to do it
在35年我们努力去做的时候
when we do really well
我们做得非常好的时候
Maybe we can do that
大概我们就可以做到这样的地步
But in 35 years
但是在35年的时间里面
The temperature of our atmosphere will increase
我们的大气的温度还会增加
our carbon dioxide
我们的二氧化碳
People are continuing our accumulation
人家在持续我们的累积
what we just saw
我们刚刚所看到的
From the atmosphere to the ocean to our subterranean world
从大气到海洋到我们的地阁
even the two armies
甚至于两军
it condition won't go away
它条件不会消失
Even in terms of Arctic ice
甚至于以北冰样来说
by this time
到了这个时候的时候
We have no ice in summer
我们夏天都已经没有冰了
so what do we have to suffer
所以我们还要承受什么
And bear with what we just saw
还要承受我们刚刚看到的
seasonal changes
季节性的变化
Heavy rain, typhoons, even volcanic earthquakes
豪大雨 台风 甚至于火山地震
And our sea level is rising rapidly
还有我们这个海平面快速上升
The impact
所带来的冲击
So what I want to tell you today is
因此我今天要告诉大家的是
absolutely simple must do
绝对简单一定要做
But don't ignore
但是更不要忽略的
That's what we're going to do now
也就是现在我们要去做的
that we're going to start doing
就是我们要开始去做
facing our natural disasters
面对我们自然灾害
every year in the future
未来每一年
We all have to face typhoons, torrential rains, flooding, mountain landslides, high temperature and heat
我們都要面對台風豪雨 淹水 山本土石流高溫熱了
The cold wave we are facing today is actually a small one
今天我們所面臨的寒潮其實都是小的
are local
都是局部的
The real shocks we face are these
我們真正面對的衝擊其實是這些
Also, our recent earthquake risk is very high
還有最近我們的地震的風險非常的高
So you must not ignore this one or two years
所以這個一兩年大家一定不要輕忽的
That is, our earthquake risk is very high
就是我們地震風險很高
we have to prepare
我們要做準備
we all hope he doesn't come
我們都希望他不要來
but we don't know if he will come
但是我們不知道他會不會來
we are not sure
我們沒有把握
The only thing we can do is to prepare for earthquakes
我們唯一可以做的就是做好防震的準備工作
More importantly, don't ignore
更重要的大家不要忽略了
before 2030
在2030年以前
If there is really no ice in Beibinyang
如果北濱陽真的沒有冰了
According to this trend
按照這個趨勢來看
It may be difficult for us to recover
我們大概很難去挽回
the sea level will rise faster
那海平面會加速上升
Our bay digs will flood
我們海灣地挖機會淹水
Increased majesty
暴消威嚴增高
We probably can't escape the large-scale semi-relocation
我們大規模半遷大概逃不掉
So if we are not ready now
所以我們現在如果不做好準備的話
the future is too late
將來是來不及的
That's what we have to face in the future
那這就是我們將來一定要去面對的
How about facing this before?
那之前面對這個呢
just tell us
就告訴我們說
We must do self-disaster, disaster prevention, disaster avoidance and disaster prevention
我們要做自災 防災 避災 就災
I share with you today
我今天跟大家分享
I accumulated all these data
我把這些數據通通累積起來
the main thing is
主要的就是
Give everyone a knowledge to build this foundation
給大家建立這個基礎的一個知識
this basic knowledge
這個基礎的知識
It's useless to know
光知道沒有用
More importantly, I hope everyone can do a good job in disaster prevention
更重要我希望大家能夠做好防災
Disaster avoidance and disaster relief work
避災跟救災的這些工作
These jobs are the most important
這些工作才是最重要的
that's here today
那今天在這個
when you come in
進來的時候
Our secretary colleagues give everyone
我們秘書同仁都給大家
will send a so-called
會發了一個所謂的
Emergency Shelter Kit Manual
緊急避難包的手冊
that besides this
那除了這個以外
In fact, our local government
其實我們的地方政府
have done some meaningful work
都做了一些很有意義的工作
Like the Taipei City Government has one
像台北市政府就有一個
Disaster Prevention Handbook for Citizens
市民防災手冊
Many people may have already downloaded
很多人可能都已經下載了
if not downloaded
如果沒有下載
You must go home today
你今天一定要回家以後
I will download this manual
我就把這個手冊下載
He put us when natural disasters happen
他把我們自然災害發生的時候
what should we do
我們該怎麼去做
how to prevent
怎麼去預防
put it all in
都把它放在裡面
integrated in
整合在裡面
Everyone must take a good look
大家一定要好好的去看
Then start to prepare for this disaster prevention
然後開始去做這個防災的準備
In the future this is September 2010
將來這是2010年9月
Flooding situation of Typhoon Vanabye in Kaohsiung
在高雄的凡納比颱風淹水的情況
will this happen
這個會發生嗎
still happens
還是會發生
And it will be better than this in the future
而且將來會比這個
More severe floods will occur
還要嚴重的水災都會發生
what is this
那這是什麼呢
This is our Taipei metropolitan area
這是我們台北都會區
Including Taoyuan around us
包括我們周圍的桃園
Our flooded landslides
我們的淹水土石流
it risks this position
它風險的這個位置
Then you can look inside your home
那你可以看你家裡面
Is it in these high-risk places?
是不是在這些風險很高的地方
if it is a high place
如果是高的地方
we take the necessary precautions
我們就採取必要的防範措施
That was March 2003
那這是2003年3月的時候
What reservoir is dry and almost no water can be seen in it?
什麼水庫乾的裡面幾乎都看不到水了
Will there be a future or will there be a future
未來會不會有 未來還是會有
It gives us the use of water resources
它給我們水資源的運用
brought a big big impact
帶來了很大很大的衝擊
Then we faced this extreme situation
那我們面對了這種極端的情況
it doesn't rain it's drought
它不下雨就是乾旱
When it rains, it rains again
一下雨的時候又是豪大雨
what should we do
我們該怎麼做
Then we actually have to start figuring out a way
那我們其實一定要開始想辦法
Recently, the New Taipei City Government and the Pingtung County Government
最近這個新北市政府跟屏東縣政府
are starting to promote the so-called sponge eco-city
都開始在推動所謂的海綿生態城市
The sponge ecological city is Professor Liu Zhongming
海綿生態城市就是柳中明教授
Like some industries, they are promoting
跟一些業界他們整個是推廣的
He made all roads into permeable roads
他把所有的道路都變成透水性的道路
when it rains heavily
就可以讓豪大雨的時候
turned into a factory facility to allow it to counterbalance
變成一個出廠的設施讓它能夠防衡
when it's not raining
在不下雨的時候
these this
這些這個
The water born under the road is our natural reservoir
道路下面出生的水就是我們天然的水庫
If you say that we put this permeable road
大家如果說是我們把這個透水性道路
only one meter
只有一公尺
Then the water permeability is only 30%
然後透水性只有30%
if our six degrees tongtong zone does
我們的六度通通區做的話
we increase the storage capacity of more than one whole reservoir
我們就增加超過一個整文水庫的蓄水量
So the benefits it brings are very, very high
所以它帶來的效益是非常非常高的
even better is
更好的是
It also has a cooling effect at high temperatures
在高溫的時候它還可以有降溫的作用
let's make our city it's not so hot
讓我們的城市它不會那麼熱
It also soothes us when the temperature is high
在溫度高的時候它讓我們也舒緩
This is what we need to do in the future
這就是我們將來需要做的
we need to turn our homes
我們需要把我們的家園
Let our country start to reduce redness towards these disaster prevention in the future
讓我們國家未來開始朝這些防災減紅
There is also the direction of high temperature resistance to strive to promote
還有抗高溫的這種方向努力去推展
our election is over
我們的選舉已經過了
But we can still tell our representatives
可是我們還是可以告訴我們的民意代表
our government officials
我們的政府官員
We must start changing the way our country is built
我們一定要開始改變我們國家的這種建設
more importantly
更重要的就是
we must not ignore
我們絕對不要忽略
Our Taiwan is a congenital earthquake is very frequent
我們台灣是一個先年性地震非常頻繁
And where the risk is very high
而且風險非常高的地方
Taiwan has so many earthquakes
台灣有這麼多的地震
These are the so-called activity components announced by the government.
這些都是政府公佈的所謂的活動成分佈的
These places tell you
這些地方都是告訴你說
don't live
不要住
why
為什麼呢
Because live bomb city is the most dangerous place
因為活彈城是最危險的地方
it's a cartoon
這是一個卡通
This cartoon tells us that
這個卡通告訴我們說
before the earthquake
在地震發生之前
where do you build a house
你在哪裡蓋房子
you feel good
你都覺得很好
But when the earthquake happened
可是當地震一發生的時候
Although Zhenyang is here
雖然震陽在這個地方
It's actually where the fault leaks that it hurts the most.
傷害最大的其實是斷層出漏的地方
because the crust shifts
因為地殼會錯動
the entire crust on both sides
整個兩邊的地殼
Its height difference will be much different
它的這個高差會差得很多
energy along the fault
能量沿著這個斷層
The place where the distribution is cast is the most
分布的地方施放是最多的
So this place hurts the most
所以這個地方傷害是最嚴重的
we can take a look
我們可以看一下
The last time this build-up earthquake
上次的這個集結地震的時候
this is the case
就是這個情況
This is the Wheel Spectrum tomography where it's located
這是車輪譜斷層它的位置
after it happened
它發生了以後
You can see it's wind source
你可以看到這是風源式
where its fault passes
它斷層經過的地方
The building responds to the sound
樓房應聲而導
If you are buying at this place
如果你是買在這個地方
There is no way to undo your damage
你的傷害是沒有辦法挽回的
This is the Tiny Wind Bridge. It's broken.
這是疲風橋它已經斷了
This is Shigang Dam
這是石崗水壩
it can't exist
它也沒有辦法存在
such a solid structure
這麼堅固的構造物
It has no way to resist the fault
它都沒有辦法抵抗斷層
let alone us
何況是我們
so be careful
所以千萬一定要注意
Our house must never be built on a fault
我們的房子絕對不可以蓋在斷層
on top of our three floors
在我們這三層的上面
how do we know
那我們怎麼知道呢
when the earthquake happened
當這個地震一發生的時候
What measures are we going to take?
我們要做的是哪些措施呢
The first one we will start ourselves
第一個我們自己就要開始
Prepare a shelter bag
準備一個避難包
Not enough for the elders in our family
不夠我們家裡面的長者
sound kid
音誘兒
and place it in an easily accessible location
然後要放在容易取得的位置
Our secretariat colleague
我們那個秘書處同仁
When our luck opened up last year
在去年我們的運氣開放的時候
I thoughtfully made this emergency for everyone
就貼心地給大家做了這個緊急
This card from the Refuge Pack
避難包的這個卡片
it tells us
裡面有告訴我們說
What kind of life support should we prepare
我們要準備哪些生命的維持
medical lighting for emergency
醫療的照明的求救的
advance letter of communication personal
預函的通訊的個人的
usually when you get ready
平常你做好準備的時候
once it happens
一旦發生的時候
you won't keep
你就不會守住無錯
And you gotta know before it happens
而且你要知道發生之前
What should we do after it happens
發生之後我們該做什麼事情
if you didn't get it just now
如果你剛剛沒拿到的
It's ok when we go out later
待會出去的時候還可以
Get another copy with our secretariat colleague
跟我們這個秘書處同仁再拿一份
This is the Zhuang'an Geological Survey Institute of the Ministry of Economic Affairs
這是經濟部莊安地質調查所
its a web page
它的一個網頁
in the upper right corner of its web page
在它的網頁的右上角
There is a country's geological regulations and customs
就有一個國土地質章俗
Integrated query system with geological data
跟地質資料整合查詢系統
You go to this page and open
你進入這個網頁 然後打開
Comb your home address in
把你家的地址梳进去
you can know your home address
你就可以知道你家的地址
Are there active faults nearby?
附近有没有活断层
Is there a downhill slope
有没有顺向坡
Are there any three risks of landslides occurring?
有没有三分土石流发生的这些风险
It's actually a really good physical exam
它其实就是一个非常好的身体检查一样
Tell us if our home is safe
告诉我们说我们的家里面安不安全
this is let us
这是让我们
Our government has integrated all these data
我们政府已经把这些资料都已经整合了
so that everyone can use
就是让大家可以使用
So you must make good use of it
所以你一定要好好去运用它
If it is not convenient for you to buy a house online
如果说是你买房子上网不方便的话
You just download the software called Di Zero Zero
你就下软体叫做地零零
put it in your phone
放在你的手机里面
Land zero zero, you just need to put it in the future
地零零你只要一放到以后
when you go to buy a house
你去买房子的时候
You stand right where your building is
你就站在你的建筑屋那个地方
it tells you if there is an active fault nearby
它就告诉你附近有没有活断层
how far is it
距离有多远
Will there be a downhill slope?
会不会有顺向坡
will there be something else
会不会有其他的东西
these are for you to tell you
这些都是让你告诉你说
Technology we can now master
我们现在可以掌握的科技
Help us avoid and prepare for these natural disasters
帮助我们去避免去防备这些自然灾害
It's actually very, very important
其实是非常非常的重要
So we now say
所以我们现在虽然说
Our environment has changed a lot
我们的环境变化很大
our risk is very high
我们的风险非常的高
But the technology we have now is unimaginable in the past
但是我们现在有的科技也是过去想象不到的
We can use this technology to protect ourselves
我们可以利用这个科技来保护自己
Now the recent central seven areas and world digital technology
现在最近中央七项区域跟天下数位科技
Another app for earthquake disaster prevention players has been developed
又发展了一个地震防灾球员的APP
Everyone can download it in your mobile phone
大家都可以在你的手机里面去把它下载
When downloading when there is an earthquake
下载的时候当一有地震
especially during earthquakes
特别是大地震的时候
it will tell you where it happened
它会告诉你说它发生在哪里
how big is it
它的规模有多大
If it happened in a place far away
如果说是发生在比较远的地方
when it happens
当它一发生的时候
can give us some early warning
就可以告诉我们一些预警
in terms of positive earthquakes
以积极地震来说
It happened on September 21, 1999 at this Nantou positive time
它在1999年9月21号发生在这个南投积极的时候
21 seconds later
隔了21秒
This destructive shock wave has only come to our Taipei
这个破坏性的震波才到我们台北来
21 seconds
这21秒
You receive it as soon as it happens
当你它一发生的时候你就接受到
You can do a lot of things in 21 seconds
21秒你可以做非常非常多的事情
So don't celebrate
所以千万不要庆负
Recently, the Fire Department of the Ministry of Earthquakes also established a Taiwan earthquake network
最近内震部消防署也建立一个台湾抗震网
So everyone can also go to the anti-seismic network
所以大家也可以到抗震网里面去
It tells us that the computer
它告诉我们说发生电脑
You must do three things well
你一定要做好三件事情
The first one must get down
第一個一定要趴下
The second is to find a place to cover early in the morning
第二個一早找地方掩護
The third must be steady
第三個一定要穩住
after the earthquake pot
地震鍋裡以後
Let's move on to the next step
我們再進行下一步的動作
in kengren.com
在坑仁網裡面
It has vibrations before we do things to prepare
它有振前我們做準備事情
How do we take refuge when it is confirmed?
證實的時候我們怎麼避難
after proof
證後的時候
what should we pay attention to
我們要注意哪些事情
even provide rescue
甚至於提供救援
it's all we can do
這都是我們可以做的
everyone must go in
大家一定要進去
then do some
然後做一些
Download this useful information
把這個有用資訊把它下載下來
Finally I want to tell you
最後我要告訴大家
you will manage money you will not be poor
你會理財 你不會窮
you can draw you can't mess
你會計畫 你不會亂
you are ready you will not be busy
你有準備 你不會忙
then i will tell you
那我也告訴大家
Facing the environmental crisis
面對環境的危機
Of course it's scary. There are many challenges.
當然很可怕 挑戰非常多
But if we are ready
可是如果我們做好準備的話
we won't die
我們就不會亡
Not only us personally
不但我們個人是這樣
Our house is still like this
我們家還是這樣的
Our country is like this
我們的國家也是這個樣子
So in the end I'll tell you
所以最後我就告訴大家說
Seven red brain words, it brings a great impact, very deep
七紅腦話它帶來衝擊很大 很深
its impact on our future
它對我們將來的這個影響
is unimaginable
是難以想像的
Our Taiwan needs each of us
我們的台灣需要我們每一個人
work together to build it
一起去努力 把它建設
make it more complete
把它變得更完整
Taiwan will definitely change in the future
台灣將來一定會改變
we can't stop
我們沒有辦法阻止
But we can be in the process of changing in Taiwan
但是我們可以在台灣改變的過程裡面
make our home
讓我們的家
Dayuan is safer
大源更安全
we are in energy
我们在能源
Food Sanitation Water quality sources
糧食 公共卫生 水质源方面
Everyone can play a force
都可以每一个人扮演一个力量
No matter what profession you do
不管你是做任何专业
you can all in this
你都可以在这方面
do our part
尽个人的一份力量
more importantly
更重要的是
Our future land plan
我们将来的国土规划
where the embankment was dug
堤挖的地方
easy place along the water
容易沿水的地方
place of fault
断层的地方
how can we avoid
我们该怎么避免
how to build
该怎么去建设
how to plan
该怎么去规划
all of us now
都是我们现在
everyone can think
每一个人都可以去思想
can work hard
可以去努力的
That's all for my sharing today
我今天的分享就到这边
Thank you very much everyone
非常谢谢大家
I also hope to bring you some connections
也希望给大家带来一些关系
i want to drink first
我想先喝口水
i don't know how
我不知道怎么样
I personally think
我个人是觉得
many friendships
会谊良多
perhaps
大概
can absorb more or less
多多少少都可以吸收一点
Then
然后
can also
也可以
do it yourself
身体力行一下
That
那
we open this now
我们现在就开放这个
please
请
i want to ask a question
我要问一个问题
that is
就是说
pacific ocean
太平洋
Continental
大陆的
actually
其实
pacific ocean
太平洋
Antarctic ice melts as temperatures rise
南極的冰因為溫度升高所以融化
Melting causes sea-level temperatures to rise
融化造成海平面的溫度上升
Then if we use another principle to deduce
那如果用另外一個原則去反推
In the 17th century in Taiwan, the temperature should have been very low
在台灣十七世紀的時候溫度應該很低
So the ice at the north and south poles melts
所以南北極的冰溶解
From these four hundred years, one thing is
從這四百年來看一件事情就是
Discovery of seawater retreat in port
發現港口的海水倒退
So in this way, the past few years
所以這樣來講的話就是說過去幾年
Is it possible for us now to let
我們現在有沒有可能讓
Taiwan returned to the temperature dropped to
台灣再回到溫度降到
Let me talk about that first, is it because
我先講那個就是說是不是因為
Diving in the port and ice in the North and South Poles
港口的遇潛跟南北極的冰
Dissolution is related
溶解有關係
Dissolving causes the water level to drop
溶解就讓水位下降
then rise
然後上升
Rising temperatures cause sea level water to rise
溫度上升就讓海平面的水上升
Is this the principle
是不是這個原理
I said you should understand
我講了應該你聽得懂
Thanks
謝謝
i need to explain
我要解釋一下
When Zheng Chenggong landed in Taiwan
當鄭成功登陸台灣的時候
At that time, it was the small soldier flag
那時候是小兵旗
Taiwan's climate is colder than ours today
台灣的氣候比我們今天還有冷
It will snow in winter
冬天都是會下雪的
like we are now
就像我們現在一樣
But after these 400 years
但是經過這400年
The influence of our braining
我們的腦化的影響
we have started
我們已經開始
It is completely different from Zheng Chenggong's era
跟鄭成功時代已經完全不一樣
At that time our Taiwan was like Kyoto today
那時候我們台灣像今天的京都
Now our Taiwan is like Manila in the past
現在我們台灣就像過去的馬尼拉
In the future we will be like this Jakarta
未來我們還會像這個亞加達一樣
So in this warming process
所以在這個暖化的過程裡面
Sea level is actually rising gradually
海平面其實是逐漸的上升
You just said that in dry mouth
你剛剛講到說在乾口裡面
we see this water level it has some changes
我們看到這個水位它有一些變化
some places will drop this
有些地方會這個下降
That has something to do with the changes in this area
那個跟這個區域的變化有關
what else
還有跟什麼呢
with our alpine one
跟我們高山那個
Chongshi related
沖石有關
let us western plains
讓我們西部的平原
Its achievements are getting wider and wider
它的這個成績就越來越廣
But now the situation has started to reverse
不過現在這個情況已經開始翻轉了
with this sea level
隨著這個海平面
rapid rise in warming
暖化快速的上升
Achievements that Takayama has enriched
高山充实下来的成绩物
Can't keep up with the rate of sea level rise
已经赶不上海平面上升的数率了
So the sea level will start flooding in the future
所以海平面将来就会开始淹过来
In fact, our current Yanchao Station
实际上以现在我们的燕潮站
Our record of real cool tests
我们真正凉测的记录
Kaohsiung Port is now a year
高雄港现在一年
What is the rate at which its seawater rises
它的海水上升的数率是多少
0.7 cm
0.7公分
The 0.4 cm we just saw
我们刚刚看到的0.4公分
Our Kaohsiung is 0.7 cm
我们高雄是0.7公分
Hsinchu cloth 1 cm
新竹呢1公分
1 year now
现在1年
Penghu is 1.7 cm
澎湖呢1.7公分
This is the Yanchao station we use now
这是我们现在用燕潮站
The observed rate of sea level rise
所看出来的海平面上升的数率
So what I'm saying is
所以我要说的是
when warming
当暖化的时候
When the edge of the two levels disappears
两级的边缘在消失的时候
Global sea levels will rise
全球的海平面都会上升
Our Taiwan is in a rising sea level
我们台湾是在一个海平面上升
relatively high place
相对比较高的地方
In the past, the climate will be cold or warm
过去的气候会有冷 会有暖
But this cyclical change is now gone
但是这种周期性的变化现在已经没有了
We only have one way now
我们现在只有有单向了
and it's getting faster
而且是越来越快
So looking at the long-term trend
所以从长期的趋势来看
The situation we are facing is completely different from the past.
我們面臨的情況跟過去已經完全不一樣了
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精彩的演講
What I want to ask is this
我想請教的是這樣子
In fact, these years
其實就是說這幾年
The warming news and scientific reports you talked about today
您今天所說的這個暖化的新聞跟科學報告等等
have heard
都有耳聞
But on the other hand, it is also heard that some scholars
但是另一方面也有耳聞說有一些學者
They claim they also present scientific evidence
他們自稱他們也提出了科學證據
say these things we face today
說我們今天面臨的這些東西
It's actually a natural part of the earth.
其實是地球自然的一環
Instead of really needing to control industry to curb desire
而不是真正需要去控制工業去抑制欲望
Be able to
才能夠
Suppressing things, so he said that everyone can continue to develop industries and continue to use energy without worrying
抑制的東西所以他是說大家不用擔心可以繼續發展工業可以繼續使用能源
but
但是
Apparently, we didn't introduce to us today what are the main views of the opposing side.
今天顯然沒有為我們介紹說反方他們的看法主要是怎麼樣
I don't know the parties, please tell us what their opinions are
不知道方方面請您為大家說一下他們有哪些看法
Then let's say your opinion is
然後我們就比方說您的意見是
How to refute their views, thank you
怎麼樣去反駁他們的這樣的看法謝謝
Go past this Cheo to warm this
再過去這個切歐暖化這個
When this issue just happened
這個議題剛剛發生的時候
That is, I just got from the institute
也就是我剛剛從研究所
when I just graduated
剛剛畢業的時候
back then we said warming
那時候我們說暖化
at a scientific meeting
在科學會議上面
our reaction
我們的這個反應
Only about 5% agree
贊成的大概只有5%
We were a minority
我們那時候是屬於少數
To this day, some people still think that
到今天還是有人認為說
warming is an illusion
暖化是一個假象
it is the natural cycle of the earth
它是地球自然循環
An important part of natural cycle changes
自然周期變化裡面重要的一環
But the remaining 5% agree
可是贊成的比例剩下5%
This endorsed has become 95%
贊證的這個已經變成95%
I just feel this warming
就是都覺得這個暖化
already a serious problem
已經是一個很嚴重的問題
it's science
這是科學上面
on this topic
在這個議題上面
we see very different
我們看到截然不同的
I'm on this topic
我在這個議題上
It's just over 30 years
也不過是30多年
I just saw it turn it over
我就看到它整個的就翻轉過來
The second means
第二個也就是說
in the history of the earth
在地球的歷史裡面
we really see
我們真的是看到
saw this it was high and low
看到了這個它有高有低
it has ups and downs
它有起伏
it has ice periods and warm periods
它有冰期有暖期
like I just showed you
就像我剛剛給大家看到的
400,000 years old record
40萬年的紀錄一樣
but it has a characteristic
可是它有個特徵
what characteristics
什麼特徵呢
it's all flat
它都是平的
because of the long-term trend
因為長期趨勢
it can go up and down
它可以高低起伏
But its trend must be flat
但是它的趨勢一定是平的
it won't have a way
它不會有一個方式
But today we see warming is not
可是今天我們看到暖化不是
Warming it really has a direction
暖化它真的是有一個方向
And there is not only one direction
而且不但有一個方向
It reverses the changes that our planet should have had
它扭轉了我們地球應該有的變化
According to this, now we understand scientifically
按照這個現在我們科學上面瞭解
If it were not for our
如果不是因為我們對於這個
environmental impact
環境所造成的影響
We changed the atmosphere inside
我們改變了這個大氣裡面
Concentration of warm oxidation
暖氧化的濃度
We should now start entering
我們現在應該要開始進入
next ice age
下一個冰期
then our weather today
那我們今天的天氣
actually better than this
其實要比這個
It's even colder when it's successful
正成功的時候還要冷還要寒
to achieve such a situation
那要達到這樣的情況
There is a very basic condition
有一個非常基本的條件
The concentration of warm oxygen in our atmosphere
我們大氣層裡面暖氧化濃度
cannot exceed 240 units
不可以超過240個單位
we can see today
我們今天可以看到
During this industrial revolution
在這個工業革命的時候
we are all here
我們都已經到了
almost 280 units
差不多將近280個單位
at that moment
在那個時候
without human influence
如果沒有人為的影響
without us causing so much disruption
沒有我們帶來這麼多的干擾的話
It will slowly drop from 280
它就會從280慢慢慢慢下降
Then as long as it reaches 240
然後只要到達240的時候
According to our current model
按照我們現在的模型
we can know that
我們就可以知道說
It's starting to enter this next ice age.
它就開始進入這個下一個冰期了
Now we don't have this chance
那現在我們已經沒有這個機會了
We are now at 400
我們現在已經到了400了
So according to the present earth
所以按照現在地球上面
This accumulated thermal energy
這個能夠累積的熱能
then it hits
然后它带来的冲击
All we can do now is say
我们现在只能够想办法说
can we do some braking
我们可不可以做一些煞车
What is the warming like today?
那今天暖化像什么呢
actually like a car
其实就像一部车
This car is not on the train tracks
这部车不是在火车的轨道上面
it is on a hillside
它是在一个山坡上面
rush down
往下面冲
Then we are actually doing the brakes now.
那我们现在其实在做煞车的动作
We want the kinetic energy of the car to go down
我们希望把这个车子往下面冲的动能
lower it
把它降低
even able to stop
甚至于能够停止
We also hope that one day it can return
我们还希望有一天它还可以回头
Now we are all here
那现在我们都是在这个
still in the downhill phase
还在下坡的阶段
So I hope everyone must work together
所以我希望大家一定要一起努力
We let this downhill rate get lower and lower
我们让这个下坡的这个速率越来越低
And hope one day it can stop
然后希望有一天它可以停
even reversed
甚至于反转
This almost changes the target to
这几乎变化的目标是
205 trips reduced to 141 meals
205旅然降为141顿
I don't have any expectations at all
我完全不抱任何的期望
because developing countries
因为开发中的国家
Absolute need to increase energy use and CO2 emissions
絕對需要增加能量的使用以及二氧化的排放
it is impossible to avoid
這是不可能避免的
Continental from 2000 to 2015
大陸從2000年到2015年
This adds 5 billion tonnes to emissions
這增加了50億噸的排放量
so like india start today
所以像印度從今天開始
I believe between 35 years
我相信35年之間
India alone will add 5 billion tonnes to emissions
光印度就要增加50億噸的排放量
and Southeast Asia
還有東南亞
there are other countries
還有其他的國家
Africa
非洲
Unless they stay forever in this inhuman life today
除非他們永遠是停留在今天這種不人道的生活
2.5 billion people in the world each year
全世界一年有25億人
Currently lives by hacking
目前是靠砍殘生活
more deaths per year
每年多死
because of climate respiratory
因為氣候呼吸道
because chopping leftovers for cooking
因為砍殘燒飯
1.5 million more deaths
多死150萬人
these poor countries
這些所貧窮的國家
They are here in 20 30 years 30 50 years
他們在這20 30年 30 50年
Must have a lot of energy usage
一定要有大量的能量使用
and produce more and more carbon dioxide
以及產生更多更多的二氧化碳
Absolutely absolutely impossible to stay at 141 tons
絕對絕對不可能停留在141噸
I can tell any of you
這一點我是可以跟各位任何一個人
I'm certainly alive until 2050
我當然活潑到2050年
I can agree with our purple grandson
我可以跟我們紫孫代達同的可以
Impossible at 141t
不可能在141噸
This is a completely unrealistic goal
這是完全不切實際的目標
and it's inhumane
而且是不人道
Those poor countries call him
那些贫穷的国家就叫他说
You can't burn briquettes if you chop stubble today
你今天砍茬就不能烧煤球
Can't burn kerosene
不能烧煤油了
You can't ride a motorcycle if you ride a cart
你骑脚拉车就不能骑摩托车了
stay in this situation forever
永远停留在这个情况
There may be more than a hundred
才可能有一百十几
This practice is completely inhumane
这个做法是完全不人道的
This is the first one
这是第一个
The second one was last year
第二个就是去年的
Because of the current cost of technology
因为现在的科技成本
The technology is quite high
科技的就是蛮高的
Losses due to natural disasters last year
去年自然灾害造成的损失
was the lowest in seven years
是七年来最低的一年
As you should know, it's only 89 billion U.S. dollars
应该你知道就890亿美金
So although the number of times reaches 1000
所以虽然次数到1000次
But property damage was the lowest in seven years.
可是财产损失是七年来最低的一次
So I think it's okay not to worry too much about these issues.
所以我认为说也不要太担心这些问题
Xia Tian said that he has not changed to one meter taller
夏天说还没变身高一公尺
I think it's probably because I personally think it's impossible to hide
我认为大概是我个人认为是躲不了的
That is 210 years more than one meter
就是210年超过一公尺
Maybe a little more, probably can't hide
大概多一点大概是躲不了
because we later
因为我们以后
It can be seen that it is always 21 billion to 31 billion
可见永远是210亿对310亿的
It is absolutely impossible to have a day of 14 billion
绝对不可能有一百四十亿的这一天
That is to say, it is impossible within fifty years
就是说五十年之内不可能
absolutely impossible
绝对不可能
And it's inhumane to ask me to say it
而且要我讲的是不人道的
you stop forcing those
你就别再强迫那些
A man who cuts his fortune will always cut his fortune, and a man who rides a bicycle will always ride a bicycle
砍財的人永遠砍財 騎腳踏車的人永遠騎腳踏車
it's impossible
這不可能事情
So what we have to do is how to say
所以我們要做的是如何說
It should be said that one meter in the future
因應說將來一公尺
In 2000 we rose one meter above the sea
2000年我們在海邊上升一公尺
We can also get a good
我們還可以獲得很好的
It's not that big of a deal, like the Dutch ones.
這個也沒大了不起 像荷蘭的
An average of one meter faster at the beach
平均在海邊快一公尺
what you should do is rich
你該做的也有錢
do what you should do
去做提防 該做這些
or content coupons
或者像內容券議
There are various ways to deal with
有各式各樣的方法可以處理
So the sea is raised by one meter
所以海邊升高一公尺
not a big problem
不是個大問題
other extreme changes in climate
其他的氣候的極端的變化
We want high mountain areas that are not suitable for people to sweep and rent horses
我們要高山地區不適合人家掃去租馬
right
對不對
it's impossible
這沒辦法的事情
What our earthquake station just said
我們地震台剛講的
If it is above the seismic station, of course the house should not be built.
如果在地震台上面當然房子不要蓋碼
So this is what we want to emphasize
所以這個是我們要強調的
But let me emphasize one more thing
可是我再加強調一條
141 tons to Master 2 in 2050
2050年141噸到2號大師
Absolutely absolutely absolutely will not bear to do it
絕對絕對絕對不忍道地去做
Thanks
謝謝
This mentions two points
這個提到兩點意見
I am very careful
我非常的注意
and also very important
而且也非常的重要
The first one is the amount of soup we will drain in the future.
那第一个就是说我们将来的排汤量
Will it reach us today
会不会达到我们今天
The goals we set at the Paris climate conference
巴黎气候大会里面我们设定的目标
Let's keep our temperature from rising two degrees
让我们的温度不要上升两度
It can even be from 1.5 degrees to 1.5 degrees.
甚至于可以从到1.5度这个样
Then let our energy saving can reach the target
然后让我们的节能节量可以达到目标
Then with the existing technology, the existing politics
那以现有的科技 现有这个政治
their mode of operation
他们的这个运作的模式
We all say it's an impossible task
我们都说这是一个不可能的任务
In fact, this is ignoring us humans
其实这是忽略了我们人类
willing to sacrifice this
愿意去牺牲的这个
You all know that we humans are like ordinary animals
你都知道说我们人跟一般的动物
The difference is
不一样的地方就是
we can change ourselves
我们可以改变我们自己
That is the game theory I just mentioned
也就是我刚刚说的那个赛局理论
What is the biggest point of Game Theory?
赛局理论最大的一个重点是什么
you have to put yourself down first
你要先放下自己
willing to sacrifice
愿意自己先牺牲
then this is paris river will it be able to pass
那这是巴黎河会它能够通过
More than 100 countries around the world can
能够让全球这100多个国家
can reach a consensus
都能够达成共识
The most important thing is that everyone is willing to compromise
最重要就是大家都愿意妥协
willing to back down
愿意退让
Compromise and retreat is just the beginning
那妥协跟退让就是一个开始
It may be difficult at first
那刚开始的时候也许比较困难
But as soon as it starts
但是只要一旦它启动
it can go in this powerful direction
它就可以往这一项有力的方向
keep moving
继续作动
so i don't think
所以我不认为
think it's an impossibility
認為說這是一個不可能的
it's a tough
這是一個艱難的
it's a very difficult goal
這是一個非常困難的目標
but not an impossible
但是不是一個不可能的
The first is to say
第一個就是說
We must strengthen the common good
我們一定要堅固公益
Just like this gentleman said
就像剛剛這位先生說的
If we only think about ourselves
如果說我們只考慮到我們自己
do not consider others
不考慮到人家
this won't work
這個不會成功
We must first consider people
我們一定要先考慮人家
just like these
就像剛剛講的這些
those poor countries
那些貧窮的那些落後的國家
if we could reach out
如果我們可以伸手
we would like to help him
我們願意幫助他
there is hope for this
那這個是有希望的
And this requires us to pay a price and sacrifice
而且這是需要我們付出代價跟犧牲的
The second is to say
第二個就是說
after warming
暖化以後
The amount of our losses will be reduced
我們的損失的金額會減少
Looks like the number of natural disasters
跟自然災害的數目看起來
Asymmetrical
不成對稱
There is actually a reason for this
這其實有一個原因
what is the reason
這個原因是什麼
because we are ready
因為我們有準備
when we are ready
當我們有準備的時候
Our damage will actually be reduced
我們的傷害其實會降低
very very many
非常非常多
Also an earthquake
同樣都是一個地震
Happened in Haiti only scale period
在海地發生只有規模期
It caused more than hundreds of thousands of casualties
它造成的傷亡是超過幾十萬人
But there was an earthquake in Chile
但是在智利發生一個地震
It scales over 8
它的規模超過8
is more than 30 times that of
是它的30倍以上
But it killed only a few hundred people
但它死亡的人數只有幾百個人
with not ready
跟沒有準備
It's the difference between good and bad construction
它的建設好跟壞這差異
So today we just want to say
那今天我們就是希望說
We wish to say that these rich and powerful countries
我們希望說這些富強的國家
well developed country
發展好的國家
be able to sacrifice a little more
能夠自己多犧牲一點
Then help these weak nations rise together
然後幫助這些弱小的國家一起起來
then our country
那我們的這個國家
There is hope in our world
我們的這個世界才會有希望
that's what i mean
這就是我是說
This requires each of us to work hard
這需要我們每一個人都去努力的
you can see
你可以看到
For example, we have a city bureau in Taiwan
譬如說我們台灣有個城局
This city bureau is here
這個城局在這個
Not the City Bureau of Kaohsiung
不是那個高雄的城局
It's the city bureau in Taitung
是那個台東的那個城局
Then it's just a vegetable seller
那它只是一個賣菜的
its impact
它帶出來的影響
can surpass many of us
可以超過我們許許多多的人
What's this
這是什麼
is that it is willing to sacrifice
就是它願意去犧牲
I think the greatest hope of our humanity today
我覺得今天我們人類最大的盼望
right here
就是在這個地方
that's what i wish to say
這就是我希望說
first of all of us
我們大家第一個
we need to know
我們要認識
It's actually today that we see this climate change
它其實今天我們看到這個氣候變化
It changes the future of our planet
它改變了我們的地球的未來
changed our lives
改變了我們的生命
it's like we got
它就像我們得到了
Cancer is not necessarily a terminal illness
都到癌症不一定是絕症
Come to cancer he will become terminally ill
來到癌症他要變成絕症
First we don't face him
第一個我們不去面對他
Second we don't treat him
第二個我們不去治療他
The third one we don't change ourselves
第三個我們不改變我們自己
so i wish to say
所以我是希望說
through a share like this
透過這樣子的一個分享
I hope you all recognize our
我希望大家認識到我們的
very challenging
挑戰很高
our difficulty
我們的難度很大
but we don't despair
但是我們沒有絕望
if we give up
如果我們放棄了
is despair
才是絕望
if we don't want to give up
如果我們不願意放棄
we are willing to sacrifice
我們願意犧牲
we are willing to reach out
我們願意伸手
we still have hope
我們還是有希望的
let's treat him
我們去治療他
we change ourselves
我們改變我們自己
we don't think it's impossible
我們不認為說這個不可能
today you can see say
今天你可以看到說
if we emit carbon
如果我們排碳
so low
降到那麼低
of course it is possible
當然是可能的
our energy
我們的能源
If new energy can be produced
如果能夠有新的能源出來
There are new efficiencies
有新的效率出來
we really can
我們真的是可以
achieve this goal
達到這個目標
This is my personal optimistic view
這是我個人樂觀的看法
so i think say
所以我認為說
Changes in our humanity
我們人類的改變
In fact, not only can
其實是不但可以
let's get there
讓我們達成目標
have a different future
有一個不一樣的未來
ask the director
請教處長
Hello everyone
大家好
My surname is Guo
我姓郭
I'm going to ask a side question first
我要先問一個附帶的問題
Have you learned about Amitou Buddha
您有沒有學阿密頭佛
this is not chinese
這不是中文
not Chinese
不是中文
I'm christian
我是基督徒
I am god
我是上帝
I'm asking this
我是要問這個
I will act first
我先行動一下
I watch TVBS TV with a few minutes of introduction
我看TVBS電視有幾分鐘的介紹
like you go to japan to flood
就像你去日本淹水
flooded the house
把房子的淹了
people standing on the roof
人家站在屋頂上
he talks more
他講的更多
He said that petrochemical leaf is a very greedy industry
他講石化葉是非常貪心的行業
There is also news in recent days
還有最近幾天也有個新聞
Said plastic bags in the ocean in a few years
說幾年以後海洋的塑膠袋
will be as much as fish
會跟魚一樣多
Look at the current situation of the color of the ocean
你看海洋成色什麼現實現況
then i have this video
那我就這個影片
I'll ask you again
我再請教你
Units like environmental scientist Lin and Academia Sinica
像環境科學家林、中研院的單位
Like Shida Environmental Pedagogy, as well as religious units
像施大環境教育學、還有宗教單位
Like Daai TV Station, Mercy Forbidden Society, and Boguang Mountain
像大愛電視台、慈禁德會、還有博光山
Many units pay great attention to the environment
很多的單位他們都非常注重環境
Environmental recycling made a lot of effort
環境回收做了很多的努力
But many units are also consuming a lot of resources
可是很多的單位也在消耗很多的資源
So the effort is wasted
所以這個努力就被消耗掉
The bottom is not enough to maintain this good environment
底下還不夠維持這個好環境
The main question I ask is to say
我請教的主要問題是說
Do you know the American government and politics?
美國的政府、政治有沒有認識
politics it is for the economic development of the country
政治它是要為國家的經濟發展
Yes, to provide the common people with a moderate life
對,要提供老百姓適度的生活
reduce employment, right?
降低就業地,對不對
This is very important
這是很重要的
the problem is to say
問題在於說
Can it be evaluated from a scientific and rational point of view?
能不能用科學理性的角度來評估
How much material resources do ordinary people need for housing and transportation?
到底老百姓十一住行要多少的物質資源
how much to produce
要生產多少東西
If there is too much consumption, it is necessary to correct it through education
如果過多的消費,就是要透過教育來導正過來
That is the question I want to ask is whether the governments, politicians, and government officials of various countries can cooperate with environmental science and religious units
那是我要請教的問題是,各國的政府、政治家、政府官員能不能配合環境科學和宗教單位
Come to the real world to educate and correct the people's thoughts and life concepts, and only then can the real environment be achieved.
來真的來教育把老百姓的思想、生活觀念導正過來,才會達到真正的環境
Then my last suggestion is that Buddhism has been spread from India to China for more than 2000 years
那我最後一個建議,就是佛教從印度傳到中國,已經2000多年了
Later, so many people in Taiwan also studied Buddhism.
後來台灣也這麼多人學佛
Let's get back to the topic, shall we?
我們回歸主題好不好
I can finish in about a minute
我大概一分鐘可以講完
you talk for five minutes
你講五分鐘
Because this is the main problem
因為這個是主要解決問題
In the 1970s, there was a British historian, Dr. Toynbee
1970年代,英國有一個歷史學家,湯恩比博士
He said that there are only two systems that can solve human problems, social problems, and earth problems in the 2 billion century
他說20億世紀的人類的問題、社會的問題、地球的問題,只有兩個系統可以解決
It is the education of Confucianism and the second Dacheng Buddhism
就是儒家的教育還有第二個大成佛教
So what does Buddhism talk about? It talks about all emptiness
那佛教講什麼?就是講一切空
No amount of development
再有多的發展都是一場空
not when people are together
人一併中的時候都沒有
I think a lot of people are raising their hands
我想還有很多人在舉手
problem first
問題先過完了
Is this good?
這樣子好不好
we can end this speech first
我們可以先結束這個演講
Then if you have any questions, you can stay and I will answer them
然後有問題的可以留下來我再回答
He just started
那剛剛他先
ask the director
請教處長
Just now we saw the whip
剛剛我們有看到圖鞭
I'm wondering if it's in the future
我在想說是不是在未來
or come again in 2016
或是再來的2016年
Earthquakes will happen in Taiwan
地震會在我們臺灣
Because of the impact of climate warming
因為氣候暖化的那個衝擊
Earthquakes will be more frequent
地震會比較頻繁
Then the haste of the earthquake will also increase, right?
然後地震的急速也會提高是不是
Thanks
謝謝
I think that from the past few decades in our
我認為說從過去我們這個幾十年來
For this area of ​​development
這個發展這個區域來說
The number of our earthquakes is increasing
我們地震的次數是在增加
But of course every year has its ups and downs
但是每一年當然都會有起伏
Then it scales
然後它的規模
So if it's a trap, will the trap grow bigger?
所以如果是陷阱 陷阱会不会变大
the world is getting bigger
全球都在变大
Taiwan will also be affected by this
我们台湾也会受到这样的影响
But will it happen in 2016
但是会不会在2016年发生
we can't say
我们不能说
because we can't predict
因为我们完全无法去预测
Let's just say it tends to look like this
我们只能说它有这样子的趋势
we must be prepared for this
我们必须做好这样子的准备
can you say this
可不可以说这个
so many people can leave first
先让很多人可以先离开
i can stay
我可以留下来
Then if there is a problem
然后有问题的话
we can be here
我们可以在这边
i want to ask a little question
我想请问一个小问题
just as said before
就是按照前面所说的
rain will increase
雨量会增加
this is a trend
这是个趋势
then ask
那请问一下
like desert areas and arid areas
像沙漠地区跟干旱地区
Is the rainfall also increasing?
是不是雨量也增加呢
or is it more arid
还是它更趋的干旱
this is a very good question
这是一个非常好的问题
Academician Liu Shaochen was here last time
上次刘少臣院士在这边
has said that he has been
已经讲说他曾经过了
we have two things to say
我们要说两件事情
First, the rainfall in global terms
第一个 雨量在全球来说的话
We don't see the obvious
我们没有明显的看到说
it is increasing
它在增加
Its most important thing is that the rainfall intensity becomes very strong
它最重要的是降雨強度變得非常的強
it gets very extreme
它變得非常的極端
Academician Liu Shaocheng used data from land
劉少成院士是用陸地上的資料
tell us the rain doesn't look like it's increasing
告訴我們說雨量看起來不增加
but i just told you
但是我剛剛告訴大家
The humidity inside our Daji City is actually a lot
我們大吉城裡面的溼度其實是大量的
So the rainfall is actually increasing
所以雨量其實是在增加
It's just that the increase doesn't necessarily happen on land
只是增加不一定發生在陸地
it may be in the sea
它可能在海裡面
So I can only say that the change of rainfall is difficult to control
所以我只能說雨量它的變化很難控制
Some places increase and some places decrease
有地方增加有地方減少
But the intensity of rainfall is increasing everywhere
但是降雨強度不管是在任何地方都在變大
Teacher, thank you for your wonderful speech today
老師謝謝你今天精彩的演講
In fact, you told us a very important concept is
其實你告訴我們一個很重要的概念就是
This group of global warming is past climate change
這個群球暖化是過去的氣候變遷
It takes tens of thousands of years and thousands of years to reach
是長達幾萬年幾千年才會達到
Now it may be reached in just a hundred years
現在可能短短的一百年就達到
This is what we have to adjust and adapt to
這是我們必須要調適跟適應的
This is our concept today
這是我們今天的概念
The most important thing is that I want to ask the teacher a few questions
最重要的是我要跟老師請教幾個問題
The first one is what you just said
第一個就剛才你談到說
Because of the relationship with Global Money
因為有Global Money的關係
So it will make Platonic Dynamic
所以會使得Platonic Dynamic
so-called plate dynamics
就是所謂的板塊動力
will intensify and cause an earthquake
就會增強而造成地震
But I don't think so
可是我覺得會不會是不是
because we have entered
是因為我們已經邁入了
Because I'm not a researcher in this area
因為我不是在這方面的研究人員
So I want to ask the teacher to say
所以我想請教老師說
When you study that terrestrial dynamics
在你研究那個地體動力的時候
Is it because our world has entered into
是不是因為我們全球已經進入到
A so-called plate activity cycle
一個所謂的板塊活動週期
And with the so-called Global Money
而跟所謂的Global Money的這個
Actually it doesn't matter
其實關係並不大
The first question I want to mention is this
我要提到第一個問題是這個
The second question is about the number of typhoons
第二個問題就是有關於台風的數量的問題
Last time Academician Liu still had that
上次劉院士還有那個
The former teacher Wu Junjie
之前那個吳俊傑老師
When they were talking about the number of typhoons
他們在談這個台風的次數的時候
actually they said
其實他們說
Emmen's theory you have already talked about
Emmen他的這個理論你們已經講到說
In fact, there is no substantial increase
其實並沒有大量的增加
What about your teacher just now?
那剛才老師你的這個
There is a large increase in the slideshow
投影片裡面有大量的增加
This is what I think is a bit of Crisis De Mar
這是我覺得有點Crisis De Mar
a problem place
的一個問題的地方
Or do we have different definitions
還是說我們對定義的不同
I will say it because you have a degree
才會說因為你有度
the number of your typhoon
你的颱風的數量
It's because your intensity definition is different
是因為你的強度定義不同
will increase or decrease
會有所增減
The third question is
第三個問題就是
Just now we talked about the rise in the temperature of the sea surface
剛才就講到海水面的溫度的上升的話
In fact, we are in the so-called
其實我們是在所謂的
In the atmosphere, we are talking next to me
在大氣裡面講我們是在溫泊我旁邊
But we found that
可是我們發現說
Next to Wen Bo me is not where the sea temperature increase is the highest
在溫泊我旁邊並不是海溫增加最高的地方
I want to ask the teacher like this
我想要請教老師這樣子
why is this the case
這為什麼是這樣的情形
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
back from the third
從第三個回頭
Mr. Liu Shaocheng, the third one listed on the market, has already said
第三個上市那個劉少成老師已經說了
Just this increase in sea temperature
剛這個海水溫度增加
Typhoons may not happen
不一定會發生颱風
It also depends on the surrounding atmospheric conditions
還要看周圍大氣的條件
For example, the wind cuts a lot
譬如說風切很多
Therefore, the sea temperature condition is only a necessary condition that he must meet.
所以海溫條件只是他必須達到的一個必要
Basic conditions but not necessarily a typhoon
基本條件但是不一定會形成颱風
In the long run, will the typhoon increase our current observation time?
長期來說颱風會不會增加我們現在觀測時間
relatively short
相對來說會比較短
so there is no definite answer
所以沒有一定的答案
Didn't I just say that
我剛剛那個不是說
i mean his
我是說他的
possible trend
可能趨勢
This is still to be verified
這還是有待驗證
so i can't say
所以我不能說
Said the typhoon will definitely increase
說颱風一定會增加
then strength it can get strong
然後強度它可以變得很強
like the typhoon we just saw
像我們剛剛看到的颱風
in terms of energy
以能量來說
what we're accumulating now on the surface
我們現在累積在地表的這些
How much is the accumulated energy in English
英文朗話說累積能量到底有多少來
I can use another number
我可以用另外一個數字
We just took the earthquake off the coast of Tohoku, Japan
我們剛剛以日本東北外海大地震的
energy scale
能量規模
How much energy do we accumulate
我們累積能量有多少個
More than 500,000
超過50萬個
Do you think it will affect our earth?
你說它會不會影響我們地球的
All Geophysical Dynamic
所有地球物理Dynamic
Right now our earth science has no answers
現在我們的地球科學沒有答案
Because our observation time is very short now
因為我們現在觀測時間很短
Our observations are not enough
我們的觀測也不足
So we don't have an answer scientifically right now
所以我們現在在科學上沒有答案
But so much energy accumulates in this place
但是這麼多能量累積在這個地方
you don't need to be precise
你不需要很精準
Let's just intuitively say
我們就從直覺來說
we know it must have had an impact
我們知道說它一定有影響
It's just that the impact with this time
只是這個影響隨著這個時間
it will become more and more obvious
它會越來越明顯
Our answers will also become clearer
我們的答案也會越來越清楚
just say that in the process
只是說在這個過程裡面
We still need to work hard to resolve
我們還是需要努力的去消解
where do they really go
那有什麼地方他們真的會去
because I watched a lot
因為我看了不少的
Yes they will come into their place
對 他們是會進入到他們的地方
they will win their place
他們會贏他們的地方
no answer
沒有答案
no answer so far
到目前沒有答案
And what we see now is all on the outermost surface of the earth
而且我們現在所看到通通在地球最表面
It's the atmosphere, the ocean and the very thin crust.
就是大氣 海洋跟非常薄的地殼
The crust is already below 100 kilometers
那地殼那個已經在100公里以下
So that's something we can't handle right now
所以那個是我們現在無法去處理的
hello teacher sorry
老師你好 對不起
i want to ask two questions
我想問兩個問題
One is that just after I heard
一個就是說剛剛我聽了以後
Knowing that carbon dioxide seems to be responsible for the entire greenhouse effect
知道二氧化碳好像是整個溫室效應的
one main reason
一個最主要的原因
Then everyone is on the same thinking of carbon dioxide
那大家都是在一致二氧化碳這個思維上面
Are there any scientific studies that say
有沒有一些科學的研究是說
For example, we are in addition to consistent carbon dioxide
比如說我們是除了一致二氧化碳以外
basically think of it as an indoor greenhouse
基本上是把它看成是一個室內溫室
Is it possible to say that there is a window on science
有沒有可能說在科學上面有一個開窗的方式
Let nature let the heat of this gas out to outer space
讓自然讓這個氣體的熱出去到外太空
Is there any research in this area so that we can come from the root
有沒有這方面的研究讓我們可以從根源來來
To reduce the possibility of this happening in HEC
來降低這個在HEC發生的可能
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question I just saw
第二個問題我剛剛看到
The teacher has a lot of data
老師有很多的數據
In this data
那這個數據裡面
It's all based on data from the past few decades.
都是從以前幾十年的數據看下來
But is there another layer
但是是不是有另外一層
For example, we lock in earthquakes above magnitude 7
比如說我們鎖定在地震是七級以上的
But various felt earthquakes below magnitude 7
可是七級以下的各種有感地震
These are all the data
這些才是全部的數據
Big data is very popular now
現在很流行大數據
Are we ignoring a section of the warning signs?
我們會不會忽略掉某一部分的警訊
on science
在科學上面
bring us meaning
帶給我們的意義
very good second question
第二個問題非常的好
We are now targeting
我們現在針對的都是
Those who have a direct impact on us at Level 7 or above
對我們直接有影響七級以上的
Earthquake below magnitude 7
七級以下的地震
Of course, its energy accumulation cannot be ignored
它的能量累積當然也不可以輕忽
This we are on science
這個我們在科學上面
Can't do it because the scale is too big
沒辦法做因為尺度太大
Our data is really not enough
我們的數據也真的不夠
Our observations are also very limited
我們觀測的也非常的有限
answer your first question
回答你第一個問題
sorry i need a moment
對不起 我要一下子
carbon dioxide
二氧化碳
carbon dioxide you just said
二氧化碳你剛剛講的
It's actually a very good idea
其實是非常好的一個創意
It's carbon dioxide and we're all one now
就是二氧化碳我們現在都變成一個
hurt us the most
對我們傷害最大
But if we can be creative
但是如果說我們能夠有創意
and then burn the carbon dioxide back
然後把二氧化碳能夠回燒
Even transforming into our creamy Nahua
甚至以轉變變成我們的奶油那化
This is actually a subject that many of us are struggling with
這是其實像我們很多人在努力探討的課題
That's actually a very good
那其實就是一個非常好的
The other is that our science uses the thermal energy accumulated on the surface of the earth
另外一個就是我們科學把現在累積在地表的這個熱能
be able to have a pipe to get it out
能夠有一個管道把它出去
That is impossible with the existing man-made technology
那以現有的人為的科技是不可能的
Only like the 311 earthquake that occurred in the northeast of Japan last time
只有像那個上次發生在日本東北歐海的311大地震
We will actually observe when the earthquake occurs
我們才會真實的觀測到那個地震發生的時候
The thermal energy of the earth's surface can go up to more than 400 kilometers outside the atmosphere
地表的熱能它可以一支的上到400多公里的大氣層外面去
This is what we can observe directly from Humanitarian Satellites
這是我們可以從人道衛星直接去觀測的
The energy it releases is something that we humans cannot achieve.
那它所釋放的能量是我們人沒有辦法去達到的
I think this earth is actually it's me tuning
我覺得這個地球其實它是我調整
It is through such an earthquake, for example
它就是藉著這樣子的一個譬如說地震
or other natural disasters that actually release energy
或者其他的自然災害其實它正在釋放能量
So the higher the energy, the more intense the earth's response
所以能量越高其實地球它的反應越激烈
Just like our high fever
就像我們這個發高燒一樣
We have to work hard to send this heat energy out
我們這個要努力的把這些熱能把它送出去
Our performance is very, very intense and extreme.
我們這個表現出來的就非常非常的激烈跟極端
Ask the teacher, I just talked about that
請教老師 剛才有談到那個
The monkey fault in Taiwan is related to sea level rise
台灣的這個猴斷層跟海平面上升的
Where are we going to find information on this?
這個我們要到哪裡去找資料
I mean it was released just now
是說剛才有放的
Can I ask the teacher to send you the materials again?
可不可以請老師再送你資料
OK, the sea level rise is currently non-existent
OK 那個海平面上升是目前是沒有的啦
That's because our current Yanchao data is actually very limited.
那因為我們現在那個燕潮的資料其實很有限
But now there is a software on the Internet
不過現在網路上面有一個軟體
This software is called a trend of sea level rise
這個軟體就叫做這個海平面上升的一個趨勢
Then you can just Google it
那你只要Google進去就可以看
it just tells you
它就告訴你說
It can only say static mock
它只能說靜態的模擬
Ascent 1 meter 2 meters 5 meters 7 meters
上升1公尺 2公尺 5公尺 7公尺
Which places will be submerged
哪些地方還會被淹沒
it's just static
它只是靜態的
it can't tell you the future
它不能告訴你說將來
By which year will it rise by how much
到哪一年會上升多少
As for the living bomb layer, it's actually very easy.
那至於活彈層其實非常的容易了
I just mentioned that there are two pages
我剛剛講到有兩個網頁
A central geological shelf lock
一個中央地質架鎖
One is ground zero zero
一個是地零零
The central geological shelf locks the information on that webpage
中央地質架鎖那個網頁裡面的資料
is very complete
是非常的完整
Then as long as you enter your home address in
那只要你把你家裡的地址輸進去
it will show you the map
它就會把地圖給你顯示出來
Then the location of active faults can be clearly marked
然後活斷層的位置可以很清楚的這個標示出來
Then you look at the distance between your home and this active fault
然後你看你的家跟這個活斷層的距離
Usually if the distance is more than 100 meters
通常如果距離在100公尺以外
you can probably rest assured
你大概就可以放心一點
If you are within this 100 meters
如果你就是在這個100公尺之內的話
you have to be careful
你要很小心
If unfortunately you happen to be on this active fault
如果不幸剛好在這個活斷層
draw the words above that line
畫那條線上面的話
I advise you to move now
我就勸你現在趕快搬家
Thank you Director Wang for your wonderful speech today
感謝王處長今天精彩的演講
Then I also brought you some messages to take home
然後也帶了大家一些帶回家的訊息
That is to say, starting from the individual and everyone to take actions to save energy and reduce carbon
就是說從個人每個人開始做節能減碳的動作
Then I just had one talking about this
那我剛剛也有一個在說這個
CO2 emissions impossible
二氧化碳排放量不可能
I said it's impossible with current technology
我說以現在的科技不可能
But you can see that many people are working hard today
可是你可以看到今天很多人在努力
we change our
我們改變我們的
Lifestyles and communities that are changing energy
生活方式還有就是改變能源的社區
If solar energy can really be developed to
如果太陽能可以真的發展到
It is indeed possible to replace our carbon dioxide
可以替代我們二氧化碳確實是可以有
Can't say it's impossible, at least it can improve
不能說不可能啦至少可以進步
don't keep going up
不要一直往上升
well thank you very much
好我們非常謝謝
thank you all
謝謝大家